<xml>
<head>
	<title>Sardanapalus</title>
<author>George Gordon, Lord Byron</author>
<pubInfo>Date first published: <date>1821</date></pubInfo>
<perfInfo>Date first performed: <date when="1834-04-10">10 Apr 1834</date></perfInfo>
</head>
<play>
<stage><strong>Scene</strong>.---A Hall in the Royal Palace of Nineveh.</stage>
<div type="act"><head>ACT I.</head>
<div type="scene"><head>Scene I.</head>
<stage>---A Hall in the Palace.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Salemenes
</speaker><stage>solus</stage>
<line><strong>He</strong> hath wronged his queen, but still he is her lord;</line>
<line>He hath wronged my sister---still he is my brother; </line>
<line>He hath wronged his people---still he is their sovereign--- </line>
<line>And I must be his friend as well as subject: </line>
<line>He must not perish thus. I will not see </line>
<line>The blood of Nimrod and Semiramis </line>
<line>Sink in the earth, and thirteen hundred years </line>
<line>Of Empire ending like a shepherd's tale; </line>
<line>He must be roused. In his effeminate heart </line>
<line>There is a careless courage which Corruption </line>
<line>Has not all quenched, and latent energies, </line>
<line>Repressed by circumstance, but not destroyed--- </line>
<line>Steeped, but not drowned, in deep voluptuousness. </line>
<line>If born a peasant, he had been a man </line>
<line>To have reached an empire: to an empire born, </line>
<line>He will bequeath none; nothing but a name, </line>
<line>Which his sons will not prize in heritage:--- </line>
<line>Yet---not all lost---even yet---he may redeem </line>
<line>His sloth and shame, by only being that </line>
<line>Which he should be, as easily as the thing </line>
<line>He should not be and is. Were it less toil </line>
<line>To sway his nations than consume his life? </line>
<line>To head an army than to rule a harem? </line>
<line>He sweats in palling pleasures, dulls his soul, </line>
<line>And saps his goodly strength, in toils which yield not </line>
<line>Health like the chase, nor glory like the war--- </line>
<line>He must be roused. Alas! there is no sound </line>
<stage>Sound of soft music heard from within.</stage>
<line>To rouse him short of thunder. Hark! the lute--- </line>
<line>The lyre---the timbrel; the lascivious tinklings </line>
<line>Of lulling instruments, the softening voices </line>
<line>Of women, and of beings less than women, </line>
<line>Must chime in to the echo of his revel, </line>
<line>While the great King of all we know of earth </line>
<line>Lolls crowned with roses, and his diadem </line>
<line>Lies negligently by to be caught up </line>
<line>By the first manly hand which dares to snatch it. </line>
<line>Lo, where they come! already I perceive </line>
<line>The reeking odours of the perfumed trains, </line>
<line>And see the bright gems of the glittering girls, </line>
<line>At once his Chorus and his Council, flash </line>
<line>Along the gallery, and amidst the damsels, </line>
<line>As femininely garbed, and scarce less female, </line>
<line>The grandson of Semiramis, the Man-Queen.--- </line>
<line>He comes! Shall I await him? yes, and front him, </line>
<line>And tell him what all good men tell each other, </line>
<line>Speaking of him and his. They come, the slaves </line>
<line>Led by the monarch subject to his slaves.</line></sp>
</div><div type="scene"><head>Scene II.</head>
<stage>Enter <strong>Sardanapalus</strong> effeminately dressed, his Head crowned with Flowers, and his Robe negligently flowing, attended by a Train of Women and young Slaves.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>speaking to some of his attendants</stage><line>Let the pavilion over the Euphrates </line>
<line>Be garlanded, and lit, and furnished forth </line>
<line>For an especial banquet; at the hour </line>
<line>Of midnight we will sup there: see nought wanting, </line>
<line>And bid the galley be prepared. There is </line>
<line>A cooling breeze which crisps the broad clear river: </line>
<line>We will embark anon. Fair Nymphs, who deign </line>
<line>To share the soft hours of Sardanapalus, </line>
<line>We'll meet again in that the sweetest hour, </line>
<line>When we shall gather like the stars above us, </line>
<line>And you will form a heaven as bright as theirs; </line>
<line>Till then, let each be mistress of her time, </line>
<line>And thou, my own Ionian Myrrha,</line>

choose;
<line>Wilt thou along with them or me?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>My Lord---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My Lord!---my Life! why answerest thou so coldly? </line>
<line>It is the curse of kings to be so answered. </line>
<line>Rule thy own hours, thou rulest mine---say, wouldst thou </line>
<line>Accompany our guests, or charm away </line>
<line>The moments from me?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					The King's choice is mine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I pray thee say not so: my chiefest joy </line>
<line>Is to contribute to thine every wish. </line>
<line>I do not dare to breathe my own desire, </line>
<line>Lest it should clash with thine; for thou art still </line>
<line>Too prompt to sacrifice thy thoughts for others.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I would remain: I have no happiness </line>
<line>Save in beholding thine; yet---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yet! what</line>
<strong>yet</strong>
?
<line>Thy own sweet will shall be the only barrier </line>
<line>Which ever rises betwixt thee and me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I think the present is the wonted hour </line>
<line>Of council; it were better I retire.</line>
<stage>Sal.
(comes forward and says)
</stage>
<line>The Ionian slave says well: let her retire.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Who answers? How now, brother?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
The
<em>Queen's</em>
brother,
<line>And your most faithful vassal, royal Lord.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>addressing his train</stage>
<line>As I have said, let all dispose their hours </line>
<line>Till midnight, when again we pray your presence. </line>
<stage>The court retiring.</stage><stage>To <strong>Myrrha</strong>, who is going.</stage>
<line>Myrrha! I thought <em>thou</em> wouldst remain.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Great King, </line>
<line>Thou didst not say so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>But</line>
<em>thou</em>
looked'st it:
<line>I know each glance of those Ionic eyes, </line>
<line>Which said thou wouldst not leave me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Sire! your brother---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>His</line>
<em>Consort's</em>
brother, minion of Ionia!
<line>How darest</line>
<em>thou</em>
name
<em>me</em>
and not blush?
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Not blush! </line>
<line>Thou hast no more eyes than heart to make her crimson </line>
<line>Like to the dying day on Caucasus, </line>
<line>Where sunset tints the snow with rosy shadows, </line>
<line>And then reproach her with thine own cold blindness, </line>
<line>Which will not see it. What! in tears, my Myrrha?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Let them flow on; she weeps for more than one, </line>
<line>And is herself the cause of bitterer tears.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Curséd be he who caused those tears to flow!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Curse not thyself---millions do that already.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Thou dost forget thee: make me not remember </line>
<line>I am a monarch.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Would thou couldst!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>My sovereign, </line>
<line>I pray, and thou, too, Prince, permit my absence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Since it must be so, and this churl has checked </line>
<line>Thy gentle spirit, go; but recollect </line>
<line>That we must forthwith meet: I had rather lose </line>
    <line>An empire than thy presence. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Myrrha</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					It may be, </line>
<line>Thou wilt lose both---and both for ever!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Brother! </line>
<line>I can at least command myself, who listen </line>
<line>To language such as this: yet urge me not </line>
<line>Beyond my easy nature.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>'Tis beyond </line>
<line>That easy---far too easy---idle nature, </line>
<line>Which I would urge thee. O that I could rouse thee! </line>
<line>Though 'twere against myself.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>By the god Baal! </line>
<line>The man would make me tyrant.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>So thou art. </line>
<line>Think'st thou there is no tyranny but that </line>
<line>Of blood and chains? The despotism of vice, </line>
<line>The weakness and the wickedness of luxury, </line>
<line>The negligence, the apathy, the evils </line>
<line>Of sensual sloth---produce ten thousand tyrants, </line>
<line>Whose delegated cruelty surpasses </line>
<line>The worst acts of one energetic master, </line>
<line>However harsh and hard in his own bearing. </line>
<line>The false and fond examples of thy lusts </line>
<line>Corrupt no less than they oppress, and sap </line>
<line>In the same moment all thy pageant power </line>
<line>And those who should sustain it; so that whether </line>
<line>A foreign foe invade, or civil broil </line>
<line>Distract within, both will alike prove fatal: </line>
<line>The first thy subjects have no heart to conquer; </line>
<line>The last they rather would assist than vanquish.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Why, what makes thee the mouth-piece of the people?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Forgiveness of the Queen, my sister wrongs; </line>
<line>A natural love unto my infant nephews; </line>
<line>Faith to the King, a faith he may need shortly, </line>
<line>In more than words; respect for Nimrod's line; </line>
<line>Also, another thing thou knowest not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What's that?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					To thee an unknown word.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yet speak it; </line>
<line>I love to learn.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Virtue.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Not know the word! </line>
<line>Never was word yet rung so in my ears--- </line>
<line>Worse than the rabble's shout, or splitting trumpet: </line>
<line>I've heard thy sister talk of nothing else.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>To change the irksome theme, then, hear of vice.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>From whom?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Even from the winds, if thou couldst listen </line>
<line>Unto the echoes of the Nation's voice.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Come, I'm indulgent, as thou knowest, patient, </line>
<line>As thou hast often proved---speak out, what moves thee?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Thy peril.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Say on.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Thus, then: all the nations, </line>
<line>For they are many, whom thy father left </line>
<line>In heritage, are loud in wrath against thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Gainst</line>
<em>me!!</em>
What would the slaves?
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					A king.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And what </line>
<line>Am I then?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					In their eyes a nothing; but </line>
<line>In mine a man who might be something still.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>The railing drunkards! why, what would they have? </line>
<line>Have they not peace and plenty?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Of the first </line>
<line>More than is glorious; of the last, far less </line>
<line>Than the King recks of.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Whose then is the crime, </line>
<line>But the false satraps, who provide no better?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And somewhat in the Monarch who ne'er looks </line>
<line>Beyond his palace walls, or if he stirs </line>
<line>Beyond them, 'tis but to some mountain palace, </line>
<line>Till summer heats wear down. O glorious Baal! </line>
<line>Who built up this vast empire, and wert made </line>
<line>A God, or at the least shinest like a God </line>
<line>Through the long centuries of thy renown, </line>
<line>This, thy presumed descendant, ne'er beheld </line>
<line>As king the kingdoms thou didst leave as hero, </line>
<line>Won with thy blood, and toil, and time, and peril! </line>
<line>For what? to furnish imposts for a revel, </line>
<line>Or multiplied extortions for a minion.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I understand thee---thou wouldst have me go </line>
<line>Forth as a conqueror. By all the stars </line>
<line>Which the Chaldeans read---the restless slaves </line>
<line>Deserve that I should curse them with their wishes, </line>
<line>And lead them forth to glory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Wherefore not? </line>
<line>Semiramis---a woman only---led </line>
<line>These our Assyrians to the solar shores </line>
<line>Of Ganges.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Tis most true. And</line>
<em>how</em>
returned?</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Why, like a</line>
<em>man</em>
---a hero; baffled, but
<line>Not vanquished. With but twenty guards, she made </line>
<line>Good her retreat to Bactria.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And how many </line>
<line>Left she behind in India to the vultures?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Our annals say not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Then I will say for them--- </line>
<line>That she had better woven within her palace </line>
<line>Some twenty garments, than with twenty guards </line>
<line>Have fled to Bactria, leaving to the ravens, </line>
<line>And wolves, and men---the fiercer of the three, </line>
<line>Her myriads of fond subjects. Is
<em>this</em>
Glory?</line>
<line>Then let me live in ignominy ever.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>All warlike spirits have not the same fate. </line>
<line>Semiramis, the glorious parent of </line>
<line>A hundred kings, although she failed in India, </line>
<line>Brought Persia---Media---Bactria---to the realm </line>
<line>Which she once swayed---and thou</line>
<em>mightst</em>
sway.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
<em>I sway</em>
them---
<line>She but subdued them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>It may be ere long </line>
<line>That they will need her sword more than your sceptre.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>There was a certain Bacchus, was there not? </line>
<line>I've heard my Greek girls speak of such---they say </line>
<line>He was a God, that is, a Grecian god, </line>
<line>An idol foreign to Assyria's worship, </line>
<line>Who conquered this same golden realm of Ind </line>
<line>Thou prat'st of, where Semiramis was vanquished.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I have heard of such a man; and thou perceiv'st </line>
<line>That he is deemed a God for what he did.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And in his godship I will honour him--- </line>
<line>Not much as man. What, ho! my cupbearer!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>What means the King?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>To worship your new God </line>
<line>And ancient conqueror. Some wine, I say.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter Cupbearer.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>addressing the Cupbearer</stage><line>Bring me the golden goblet thick with gems, </line>
<line>Which bears the name of Nimrod's chalice. Hence, </line>
<line>Fill full, and bear it quickly. </line></sp>
<stage>Exit Cupbearer.</stage><sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Is this moment </line>
<line>A fitting one for the resumption of </line>
<line>Thy yet unslept-off revels?</line>
</sp><stage>Re-enter Cupbearer, with wine.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>taking the cup from him</stage>
<line>					Noble kinsman, </line>
<line>If these barbarian Greeks of the far shores </line>
<line>And skirts of these our realms lie not, this Bacchus </line>
<line>Conquered the whole of India, did he not?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>He did, and thence was deemed a Deity.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Not so:---of all his conquests a few columns. </line>
<line>Which may be his, and might be mine, if I </line>
<line>Thought them worth purchase and conveyance, are </line>
<line>The landmarks of the seas of gore he shed, </line>
<line>The realms he wasted, and the hearts he broke. </line>
<line>But here---here in this goblet is his title </line>
<line>To immortality---the immortal grape </line>
<line>From which he first expressed the soul, and gave </line>
<line>To gladden that of man, as some atonement </line>
<line>For the victorious mischiefs he had done. </line>
<line>Had it not been for this, he would have been </line>
<line>A mortal still in name as in his grave; </line>
<line>And, like my ancestor Semiramis, </line>
<line>A sort of semi-glorious human monster. </line>
<line>Here's that which deified him---let it now </line>
<line>Humanise thee; my surly, chiding brother, </line>
<line>Pledge me to the Greek God!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					For all thy realms </line>
<line>I would not so blaspheme our country's creed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That is to say, thou thinkest him a hero, </line>
<line>That he shed blood by oceans; and no God, </line>
<line>Because he turned a fruit to an enchantment, </line>
<line>Which cheers the sad, revives the old, inspires </line>
<line>The young, makes Weariness forget his toil, </line>
<line>And Fear her danger; opens a new world </line>
<line>When this, the present, palls. Well, then <em>I</em> pledge thee</line>
<line>And <em>him</em> as a true man, who did his utmost</line>
<line>In good or evil to surprise mankind. </line></sp>
<stage>Drinks.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Wilt thou resume a revel at this hour?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And if I did, 'twere better than a trophy, </line>
<line>Being bought without a tear. But that is not </line>
<line>My present purpose: since thou wilt not pledge me, </line>
<line>Continue what thou pleasest.</line>
    <stage>To the Cupbearer.</stage><line>Boy, retire.</line></sp>
<stage>Exit Cupbearer.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I would but have recalled thee from thy dream; </line>
<line>Better by me awakened than rebellion.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Who should rebel? or why? what cause? pretext? </line>
<line>I am the lawful King, descended from </line>
<line>A race of Kings who knew no predecessors. </line>
<line>What have I done to thee, or to the people, </line>
<line>That thou shouldst rail, or they rise up against me?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Of what thou hast done to me, I speak not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>But </line>
<line>Thou think'st that I have wronged the Queen: is't not so?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker><em>Think!</em>
Thou hast wronged her!
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Patience, Prince, and hear me. </line>
<line>She has all power and splendour of her station, </line>
<line>Respect, the tutelage of Assyria's heirs, </line>
<line>The homage and the appanage of sovereignty. </line>
<line>I married her as monarchs wed---for state, </line>
<line>And loved her as most husbands love their wives. </line>
<line>If she or thou supposedst I could link me </line>
<line>Like a Chaldean peasant to his mate, </line>
<line>Ye knew nor me---nor monarchs---nor mankind.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I pray thee, change the theme: my blood disdains </line>
<line>Complaint, and Salemenes' sister seeks not </line>
<line>Reluctant love even from Assyria's lord! </line>
<line>Nor would she deign to accept divided passion </line>
<line>With foreign strumpets and Ionian slaves. </line>
<line>The Queen is silent.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And why not her brother?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I only echo thee the voice of empires, </line>
<line>Which he who long neglects not long will govern.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>The ungrateful and ungracious slaves! they murmur </line>
<line>Because I have not shed their blood, nor led them </line>
<line>To dry into the desert's dust by myriads, </line>
<line>Or whiten with their bones the banks of Ganges; </line>
<line>Nor decimated them with savage laws, </line>
<line>Nor sweated them to build up Pyramids, </line>
<line>Or Babylonian walls.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Yet these are trophies </line>
<line>More worthy of a people and their prince </line>
<line>Than songs, and lutes, and feasts, and concubines, </line>
<line>And lavished treasures, and contemnéd virtues.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Or for my trophies I have founded cities: </line>
<line>There's Tarsus and Anchialus, both built </line>
<line>In one day---what could that blood-loving beldame, </line>
<line>My martial grandam, chaste Semiramis, </line>
<line>Do more, except destroy them?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis most true; </line>
<line>I own thy merit in those founded cities, </line>
<line>Built for a whim, recorded with a verse </line>
<line>Which shames both them and thee to coming ages.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Shame me! By Baal, the cities, though well built, </line>
<line>Are not more goodly than the verse! Say what </line>
<line>Thou wilt 'gainst me, my mode of life or rule, </line>
<line>But nothing 'gainst the truth of that brief record. </line>
<line>Why, those few lines contain the history </line>
<line>Of all things human: hear---"Sardanapalus, </line>
<line>The king, and son of Anacyndaraxes, </line>
<line>In one day built Anchialus and Tarsus. </line>
<line>Eat, drink, and love; the rest's not worth a fillip."</line>

</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>A worthy moral, and a wise inscription, </line>
<line>For a king to put up before his subjects!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Oh, thou wouldst have me doubtless set up edicts--- </line>
<line>"Obey the king---contribute to his treasure--- </line>
<line>Recruit his phalanx---spill your blood at bidding--- </line>
<line>Fall down and worship, or get up and toil." </line>
<line>Or thus---"Sardanapalus on this spot </line>
<line>Slew fifty thousand of his enemies. </line>
<line>These are their sepulchres, and this his trophy." </line>
<line>I leave such things to conquerors; enough </line>
<line>For me, if I can make my subjects feel </line>
<line>The weight of human misery less, and glide </line>
<line>Ungroaning to the tomb: I take no license </line>
<line>Which I deny to them. We all are men.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Thy Sires have been revered as Gods---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>In dust </line>
<line>And death, where they are neither Gods nor men. </line>
<line>Talk not of such to me! the worms are Gods; </line>
<line>At least they banqueted upon your Gods, </line>
<line>And died for lack of farther nutriment. </line>
<line>Those Gods were merely men; look to their issue--- </line>
<line>I feel a thousand mortal things about me, </line>
<line>But nothing godlike,---unless it may be </line>
<line>The thing which you condemn, a disposition </line>
<line>To love and to be merciful, to pardon </line>
<line>The follies of my species, and (that's human) </line>
<line>To be indulgent to my own.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Alas! </line>
<line>The doom of Nineveh is sealed.---Woe---woe </line>
<line>To the unrivalled city!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What dost dread?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Thou art guarded by thy foes: in a few hours </line>
<line>The tempest may break out which overwhelms thee, </line>
<line>And thine and mine; and in another day</line> 
<line>What <em>is</em> shall be the past of Belus' race.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What must we dread?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Ambitious treachery, </line>
<line>Which has environed thee with snares; but yet </line>
<line>There is resource: empower me with thy signet </line>
<line>To quell the machinations, and I lay </line>
<line>The heads of thy chief foes before thy feet.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>The heads---how many?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Must I stay to number </line>
<line>When even thine own's in peril? Let me go; </line>
<line>Give me thy signet---trust me with the rest.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I will trust no man with unlimited lives. </line>
<line>When we take those from others, we nor know </line>
<line>What we have taken, nor the thing we give.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Wouldst thou not take their lives who seek for thine?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That's a hard question---But I answer, Yes. </line>
<line>Cannot the thing be done without? Who are they </line>
<line>Whom thou suspectest?---Let them be arrested.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I would thou wouldst not ask me; the next moment </line>
<line>Will send my answer through thy babbling troop </line>
<line>Of paramours, and thence fly o'er the palace, </line>
<line>Even to the city, and so baffle all.--- </line>
<line>Trust me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Thou knowest I have done so ever; </line>
<line>Take thou the signet. </line></sp>
<stage>Gives the signet.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					I have one more request.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Name it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					That thou this night forbear the banquet </line>
<line>In the pavilion over the Euphrates.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Forbear the banquet! Not for all the plotters </line>
<line>That ever shook a kingdom! Let them come, </line>
<line>And do their worst: I shall not blench for them; </line>
<line>Nor rise the sooner; nor forbear the goblet; </line>
<line>Nor crown me with a single rose the less; </line>
<line>Nor lose one joyous hour.---I fear them not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>But thou wouldst arm thee, wouldst thou not, if needful?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Perhaps. I have the goodliest armour, and </line>
<line>A sword of such a temper, and a bow, </line>
<line>And javelin, which might furnish Nimrod forth: </line>
<line>A little heavy, but yet not unwieldy. </line>
<line>And now I think on't, 'tis long since I've used them, </line>
<line>Even in the chase. Hast ever seen them, brother?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Is this a time for such fantastic trifling?--- </line>
<line>If need be, wilt thou wear them?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Will I not? </line>
<line>Oh! if it must be so, and these rash slaves </line>
<line>Will not be ruled with less, I'll use the sword </line>
<line>Till they shall wish it turned into a distaff.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>They say thy Sceptre's turned to that already.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That's false! but let them say so: the old Greeks, </line>
<line>Of whom our captives often sing, related </line>
<line>The same of their chief hero, Hercules, </line>
<line>Because he loved a Lydian queen: thou seest </line>
<line>The populace of all the nations seize </line>
<line>Each calumny they can to sink their sovereigns.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>They did not speak thus of thy fathers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					No; </line>
<line>They dared not. They were kept to toil and combat; </line>
<line>And never changed their chains but for their armour: </line>
<line>Now they have peace and pastime, and the license </line>
<line>To revel and to rail; it irks me not. </line>
<line>I would not give the smile of one fair girl </line>
<line>For all the popular breath that e'er divided </line>
<line>A name from nothing. What are the rank tongues </line>
<line>Of this vile herd, grown insolent with feeding, </line>
<line>That I should prize their noisy praise, or dread </line>
<line>Their noisome clamour?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>You have said they are men; </line>
<line>As such their hearts are something.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>So my dogs' are; </line>
<line>And better, as more faithful:---but, proceed; </line>
<line>Thou hast my signet:---since they are tumultuous, </line>
<line>Let them be tempered, yet not roughly, till </line>
<line>Necessity enforce it. I hate all pain, </line>
<line>Given or received; we have enough within us, </line>
<line>The meanest vassal as the loftiest monarch, </line>
<line>Not to add to each other's natural burthen </line>
<line>Of mortal misery, but rather lessen, </line>
<line>By mild reciprocal alleviation, </line>
<line>The fatal penalties imposed on life: </line>
<line>But this they know not, or they will not know. </line>
<line>I have, by Baal! done all I could to soothe them: </line>
<line>I made no wars, I added no new imposts, </line>
<line>I interfered not with their civic lives, </line>
<line>I let them pass their days as best might suit them, </line>
<line>Passing my own as suited me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Thou stopp'st </line>
<line>Short of the duties of a king; and therefore </line>
<line>They say thou art unfit to be a monarch.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>They lie.---Unhappily, I am unfit </line>
<line>To be aught save a monarch; else for me </line>
<line>The meanest Mede might be the king instead.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>There is one Mede, at least, who seeks to be so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What mean'st thou!---'tis thy secret; thou desirest </line>
<line>Few questions, and I'm not of curious nature. </line>
<line>Take the fit steps; and, since necessity </line>
<line>Requires, I sanction and support thee. Ne'er </line>
<line>Was man who more desired to rule in peace </line>
<line>The peaceful only: if they rouse me, better </line>
<line>They had conjured up stern Nimrod from his ashes, </line>
<line>"The Mighty Hunter!" I will turn these realms </line>
<line>To one wide desert chase of brutes, who <em>were</em>,</line>
<line>But <em>would</em> no more, by their own choice, be human.</line>
<line><em>What</em> they have found me, they belie; <em>that which</em></line>
<line>They yet may find me---shall defy their wish </line>
<line>To speak it worse; and let them thank themselves.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Then thou at last canst feel?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Feel! who feels not </line>
<line>Ingratitude?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I will not pause to answer </line>
<line>With words, but deeds. Keep thou awake that energy </line>
<line>Which sleeps at times, but is not dead within thee, </line>
<line>And thou may'st yet be glorious in thy reign, </line>
<line>As powerful in thy realm. Farewell! </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>solus</stage>
<line>					Farewell! </line>
<line>He's gone; and on his finger bears my signet, </line>
<line>Which is to him a sceptre. He is stern </line>
<line>As I am heedless; and the slaves deserve </line>
<line>To feel a master. What may be the danger, </line>
<line>I know not: he hath found it, let him quell it. </line>
<line>Must I consume my life---this little life--- </line>
<line>In guarding against all may make it less? </line>
<line>It is not worth so much! It were to die </line>
<line>Before my hour, to live in dread of death, </line>
<line>Tracing revolt; suspecting all about me, </line>
<line>Because they are near; and all who are remote, </line>
<line>Because they are far. But if it should be so--- </line>
<line>If they should sweep me off from Earth and Empire, </line>
<line>Why, what is Earth or Empire of the Earth? </line>
<line>I have loved, and lived, and multiplied my image; </line>
<line>To die is no less natural than those </line>
<line>Acts of this clay! 'Tis true I have not shed </line>
<line>Blood as I might have done, in oceans, till </line>
<line>My name became the synonyme of Death--- </line>
<line>A terror and a trophy. But for this </line>
<line>I feel no penitence; my life is love: </line>
<line>If I must shed blood, it shall be by force. </line>
<line>Till now, no drop from an Assyrian vein </line>
<line>Hath flowed for me, nor hath the smallest coin </line>
<line>Of Nineveh's vast treasures e'er been lavished </line>
<line>On objects which could cost her sons a tear: </line>
<line>If then they hate me, 'tis because I hate not: </line>
<line>If they rebel, 'tis because I oppress not. </line>
<line>Oh, men! ye must be ruled with scythes, not sceptres, </line>
<line>And mowed down like the grass, else all we reap </line>
<line>Is rank abundance, and a rotten harvest </line>
<line>Of discontents infecting the fair soil, </line>
<line>Making a desert of fertility.--- </line>
<line>I'll think no more.---Within there, ho!</line></sp>
<stage>Enter an <strong>Attendant</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Slave, tell </line>
<line>The Ionian Myrrha we would crave her presence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Attend.</speaker>
<line>King, she is here.</line></sp>
<stage><strong>Myrrha</strong> enters.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>apart to Attendant</stage>
<line>					Away!</line>
<stage>Addressing <strong>Myrrha</strong>.</stage>
<line>Beautiful being!</line> 
<line>Thou dost almost anticipate my heart; </line>
<line>It throbbed for thee, and here thou comest: let me </line>
<line>Deem that some unknown influence, some sweet oracle, </line>
<line>Communicates between us, though unseen, </line>
<line>In absence, and attracts us to each other.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>There doth.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I know there doth, but not its name: </line>
<line>What is it?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>In my native land a God, </line>
<line>And in my heart a feeling like a God's, </line>
<line>Exalted; yet I own 'tis only mortal; </line>
<line>For what I feel is humble, and yet happy--- </line>
<line>That is, it would be happy; but--- </line></sp>
<stage><strong>[Myrrha</strong> pauses.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					There comes </line>
<line>For ever something between us and what </line>
<line>We deem our happiness: let me remove </line>
<line>The barrier which that hesitating accent </line>
<line>Proclaims to thine, and mine is sealed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>My Lord!---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My Lord---my King---Sire---Sovereign; thus it is--- </line>
<line>For ever thus, addressed with awe. I ne'er </line>
<line>Can see a smile, unless in some broad banquet's </line>
<line>Intoxicating glare, when the buffoons </line>
<line>Have gorged themselves up to equality, </line>
<line>Or I have quaffed me down to their abasement. </line>
<line>Myrrha, I can hear all these things, these names, </line>
<line>Lord---King---Sire---Monarch---nay, time was I prized them; </line>
<line>That is, I suffered them---from slaves and nobles; </line>
<line>But when they falter from the lips I love, </line>
<line>The lips which have been pressed to mine, a chill </line>
<line>Comes o'er my heart, a cold sense of the falsehood </line>
<line>Of this my station, which represses feeling </line>
<line>In those for whom I have felt most, and makes me </line>
<line>Wish that I could lay down the dull tiara, </line>
<line>And share a cottage on the Caucasus </line>
<line>With thee---and wear no crowns but those of flowers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Would that we could!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And dost</line>
<em>thou</em>
feel this?---Why?</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Then thou wouldst know what thou canst never know.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And that is---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>The true value of a heart; </line>
<line>At least, a woman's.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I have proved a thousand--- </line>
<line>A thousand, and a thousand.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Hearts?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I think so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Not one! the time may come thou may'st.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					It will. </line>
<line>Hear, Myrrha; Salemenes has declared--- </line>
<line>Or why or how he hath divined it, Belus, </line>
<line>Who founded our great realm, knows more than I--- </line>
<line>But Salemenes hath declared my throne </line>
<line>In peril.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>He did well.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And say'st</line>
<em>thou</em>
so?
<line>Thou whom he spurned so harshly, and now dared </line>
<line>Drive from our presence with his savage jeers, </line>
<line>And made thee weep and blush?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I should do both </line>
<line>More frequently, and he did well to call me </line>
<line>Back to my duty. But thou spakest of peril </line>
<line>Peril to thee---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Aye, from dark plots and snares </line>
<line>From Medes---and discontented troops and nations. </line>
<line>I know not what---a labyrinth of things--- </line>
<line>A maze of muttered threats and mysteries: </line>
<line>Thou know'st the man---it is his usual custom. </line>
<line>But he is honest. Come, we'll think no more on't--- </line>
<line>But of the midnight festival.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>'Tis time </line>
<line>To think of aught save festivals. Thou hast not </line>
<line>Spurned his sage cautions?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What?---and dost thou fear?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Fear!---I'm a Greek, and how should I fear death? </line>
<line>A slave, and wherefore should I dread my freedom?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then wherefore dost thou turn so pale?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I love.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And do not I? I love thee far---far more </line>
<line>Than either the brief life or the wide realm, </line>
<line>Which, it may be, are menaced;---yet I blench not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>That means thou lovest nor thyself nor me; </line>
<line>For he who loves another loves himself, </line>
<line>Even for that other's sake. This is too rash: </line>
<line>Kingdoms and lives are not to be so lost.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Lost!---why, who is the aspiring chief who dared </line>
<line>Assume to win them?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Who is he should dread </line>
<line>To try so much? When he who is their ruler </line>
<line>Forgets himself---will they remember him?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Myrrha!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Frown not upon me: you have smiled </line>
<line>Too often on me not to make those frowns </line>
<line>Bitterer to bear than any punishment </line>
<line>Which they may augur.---King, I am your subject! </line>
<line>Master, I am your slave! Man, I have loved you!--- </line>
<line>Loved you, I know not by what fatal weakness, </line>
<line>Although a Greek, and born a foe to monarchs--- </line>
<line>A slave, and hating fetters---an Ionian, </line>
<line>And, therefore, when I love a stranger, more </line>
<line>Degraded by that passion than by chains! </line>
<line>Still I have loved you. If that love were strong </line>
<line>Enough to overcome all former nature, </line>
<line>Shall it not claim the privilege to save you?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker><em>Save</em>
me, my beauty! Thou art very fair,
<line>And what I seek of thee is love---not safety.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And without love where dwells security?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I speak of woman's love.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					The very first </line>
<line>Of human life must spring from woman's breast, </line>
<line>Your first small words are taught you from her lips, </line>
<line>Your first tears quenched by her, and your last sighs </line>
<line>Too often breathed out in a woman's hearing, </line>
<line>When men have shrunk from the ignoble care </line>
<line>Of watching the last hour of him who led them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My eloquent Ionian! thou speak'st music: </line>
<line>The very chorus of the tragic song </line>
<line>I have heard thee talk of as the favourite pastime </line>
<line>Of thy far father-land. Nay, weep not---calm thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I weep not.---But I pray thee, do not speak </line>
<line>About my fathers or their land.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yet oft </line>
<line><em>Thou</em> speakest of them.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>True---true: constant thought </line>
<line>Will overflow in words unconsciously; </line>
<line>But when another speaks of Greeks, it wounds me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Well, then, how wouldst thou</line>
<em>save</em>
me, as thou saidst?
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>By teaching thee to save thyself, and not </line>
<line>Thyself alone, but these vast realms, from all </line>
<line>The rage of the worst war---the war of brethren.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Why, child, I loathe all war, and warriors; </line>
<line>I live in peace and pleasure: what can man </line>
<line>Do more?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Alas! my Lord, with common men </line>
<line>There needs too oft the show of war to keep </line>
<line>The substance of sweet peace; and, for a king, </line>
<line>'Tis sometimes better to be feared than loved.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And I have never sought but for the last.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And now art neither.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Dost</line>
<em>thou</em>
say so, Myrrha?</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I speak of civic popular love,</line>
<em>self</em>
-love,
<line>Which means that men are kept in awe and law, </line>
<line>Yet not oppressed---at least they must not think so, </line>
<line>Or, if they think so, deem it necessary, </line>
<line>To ward off worse oppression, their own passions. </line>
<line>A King of feasts, and flowers, and wine, and revel, </line>
<line>And love, and mirth, was never King of Glory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Glory! what's that?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Ask of the Gods thy fathers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>They cannot answer; when the priests speak for them, </line>
<line>'Tis for some small addition to the temple.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Look to the annals of thine Empire's founders.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>They are so blotted o'er with blood, I cannot. </line>
<line>But what wouldst have? the Empire <em>has been</em> founded.</line>
<line>I cannot go on multiplying empires.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Preserve thine own.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>At least, I will enjoy it. </line>
<line>Come, Myrrha, let us go on to the Euphrates: </line>
<line>The hour invites, the galley is prepared, </line>
<line>And the pavilion, decked for our return, </line>
<line>In fit adornment for the evening banquet, </line>
<line>Shall blaze with beauty and with light, until </line>
<line>It seems unto the stars which are above us </line>
<line>Itself an opposite star; and we will sit </line>
<line>Crowned with fresh flowers like---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Victims.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No, like sovereigns, </line>
<line>The Shepherd Kings of patriarchal times, </line>
<line>Who knew no brighter gems than summer wreaths, </line>
<line>And none but tearless triumphs. Let us on.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Pania</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>May the King live for ever!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Not an hour </line>
<line>Longer than he can love. How my soul hates </line>
<line>This language, which makes life itself a lie, </line>
<line>Flattering dust with eternity. Well, Pania! </line>
<line>Be brief.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>I am charged by Salemenes to </line>
<line>Reiterate his prayer unto the King, </line>
<line>That for this day, at least, he will not quit </line>
<line>The palace: when the General returns, </line>
<line>He will adduce such reasons as will warrant </line>
<line>His daring, and perhaps obtain the pardon </line>
<line>Of his presumption.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What! am I then cooped? </line>
<line>Already captive? can I not even breathe </line>
<line>The breath of heaven? Tell prince Salemenes, </line>
<line>Were all Assyria raging round the walls </line>
<line>In mutinous myriads, I would still go forth.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>I must obey, and yet---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Oh, Monarch, listen.--- </line>
<line>How many a day and moon thou hast reclined </line>
<line>Within these palace walls in silken dalliance, </line>
<line>And never shown thee to thy people's longing; </line>
<line>Leaving thy subjects' eyes ungratified, </line>
<line>The satraps uncontrolled, the Gods unworshipped, </line>
<line>And all things in the anarchy of sloth, </line>
<line>Till all, save evil, slumbered through the realm! </line>
<line>And wilt thou not now tarry for a day,--- </line>
<line>A day which may redeem thee? Wilt thou not </line>
<line>Yield to the few still faithful a few hours, </line>
<line>For them, for thee, for thy past fathers' race, </line>
<line>And for thy sons' inheritance?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>'Tis true! </line>
<line>From the deep urgency with which the Prince </line>
<line>Despatched me to your sacred presence, I </line>
<line>Must dare to add my feeble voice to that </line>
<line>Which now has spoken.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No, it must not be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>For the sake of thy realm!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Away!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>For that </line>
<line>Of all thy faithful subjects, who will rally </line>
<line>Round thee and thine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>These are mere fantasies: </line>
<line>There is no peril:---'tis a sullen scheme </line>
<line>Of Salemenes, to approve his zeal, </line>
<line>And show himself more necessary to us.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>			By all that's good and glorious take this counsel.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Business to-morrow.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Aye---or death to-night.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Why let it come then unexpectedly, </line>
<line>'Midst joy and gentleness, and mirth and love; </line>
<line>So let me fall like the plucked rose!---far better </line>
<line>Thus than be withered.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Then thou wilt not yield, </line>
<line>Even for the sake of all that ever stirred </line>
<line>A monarch into action, to forego </line>
<line>A trifling revel.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Then yield for</line>
<em>mine</em>
;
<line>For my sake!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Thine, my Myrrha!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>'Tis the first </line>
<line>Boon which I ever asked Assyria's king.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That's true, and, wer't my kingdom, must be granted. </line>
<line>Well, for thy sake, I yield me. Pania, hence! </line>
<line>Thou hear'st me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					And obey. </line>
<line>				Exit</line>
<strong>Pania</strong>
.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I marvel at thee. </line>
<line>What is thy motive, Myrrha, thus to urge me?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Thy safety; and the certainty that nought </line>
<line>Could urge the Prince thy kinsman to require </line>
<line>Thus much from thee, but some impending danger.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And if I do not dread it, why shouldst thou?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Because</line>
<em>thou</em>
dost not fear, I fear for
<em>thee</em>
.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>To-morrow thou wilt smile at these vain fancies.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>If the worst come, I shall be where none weep, </line>
<line>And that is better than the power to smile. </line>
<line>And thou?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I shall be King, as heretofore.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Where?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					With Baal, Nimrod, and Semiramis, </line>
<line>Sole in Assyria, or with them elsewhere. </line>
<line>Fate made me what I am---may make me nothing--- </line>
<line>But either that or nothing must I be: </line>
<line>I will not live degraded.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Hadst thou felt </line>
<line>Thus always, none would ever dare degrade thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And who will do so now?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Dost thou suspect none?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Suspect!---that's a spy's office. Oh! we lose </line>
<line>Ten thousand precious moments in vain words, </line>
<line>And vainer fears. Within there!---ye slaves, deck </line>
<line>The Hall of Nimrod for the evening revel; </line>
<line>If I must make a prison of our palace, </line>
<line>At least we'll wear our fetters jocundly; </line>
<line>If the Euphrates be forbid us, and </line>
<line>The summer-dwelling on its beauteous border, </line>
<line>Here we are still unmenaced. Ho! within there!</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Sardanapalus</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>
Myr.
</speaker><stage>solus</stage><line>Why do I love this man? My country's daughters </line>
<line>Love none but heroes. But I have no country! </line>
<line>The slave hath lost all save her bonds. I love him; </line>
<line>And that's the heaviest link of the long chain--- </line>
<line>To love whom we esteem not. Be it so: </line>
<line>The hour is coming when he'll need all love, </line>
<line>And find none. To fall from him now were baser </line>
<line>Than to have stabbed him on his throne when highest </line>
<line>Would have been noble in my country's creed: </line>
<line>I was not made for either. Could I save him,</line> 
<line>I should not love <em>him</em> better, but myself;</line>
<line>And I have need of the last, for I have fallen </line>
<line>In my own thoughts, by loving this soft stranger: </line>
<line>And yet, methinks, I love him more, perceiving </line>
<line>That he is hated of his own barbarians, </line>
<line>The natural foes of all the blood of Greece. </line>
<line>Could I but wake a single thought like those </line>
<line>Which even the Phrygians felt when battling long </line>
<line>'Twixt Ilion and the sea, within his heart, </line>
<line>He would tread down the barbarous crowds, and triumph. </line>
<line>He loves me, and I love him; the slave loves </line>
<line>Her master, and would free him from his vices. </line>
<line>If not, I have a means of freedom still, </line>
<line>And if I cannot teach him how to reign, </line>
<line>May show him how alone a King can leave </line>
<line>His throne. I must not lose him from my sight.</line></sp>
<stage>Exit.</stage>
</div>
</div><div type="act"><head>ACT II.</head>
<div type="scene"><head>Scene I.</head>
<stage>---The Portal of the same Hall of the Palace.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Beleses
</speaker><stage>solus</stage><line>The Sun goes down: methinks he sets more slowly, </line>
<line>Taking his last look of Assyria's Empire. </line>
<line>How red he glares amongst those deepening clouds, </line>
<line>Like the blood he predicts. If not in vain, </line>
<line>Thou Sun that sinkest, and ye stars which rise, </line>
<line>I have outwatched ye, reading ray by ray </line>
<line>The edicts of your orbs, which make Time tremble </line>
<line>For what he brings the nations, 'tis the furthest </line>
<line>Hour of Assyria's years. And yet how calm! </line>
<line>An earthquake should announce so great a fall--- </line>
<line>A summer's sun discloses it. Yon disk, </line>
<line>To the star-read Chaldean, bears upon </line>
<line>Its everlasting page the end of what </line>
<line>Seemed everlasting; but oh! thou true Sun! </line>
<line>The burning oracle of all that live, </line>
<line>As fountain of all life, and symbol of </line>
<line>Him who bestows it, wherefore dost thou limit </line>
<line>Thy lore unto calamity? Why not </line>
<line>Unfold the rise of days more worthy thine </line>
<line>All-glorious burst from ocean? why not dart </line>
<line>A beam of hope athwart the future years, </line>
<line>As of wrath to its days? Hear me! oh, hear me! </line>
<line>I am thy worshipper, thy priest, thy servant--- </line>
<line>I have gazed on thee at thy rise and fall, </line>
<line>And bowed my head beneath thy mid-day beams, </line>
<line>When my eye dared not meet thee. I have watched </line>
<line>For thee, and after thee, and prayed to thee, </line>
<line>And sacrificed to thee, and read, and feared thee, </line>
<line>And asked of thee, and thou hast answered---but </line>
<line>Only to thus much: while I speak, he sinks--- </line>
<line>Is gone---and leaves his beauty, not his knowledge, </line>
<line>To the delighted West, which revels in </line>
<line>Its hues of dying glory. Yet what is </line>
<line>Death, so it be but glorious? 'Tis a sunset; </line>
<line>And mortals may be happy to resemble </line>
<line>The Gods but in decay.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Arbaces</strong> by an inner door</stage>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					Beleses, why </line>
<line>So wrapt in thy devotions? Dost thou stand </line>
<line>Gazing to trace thy disappearing God </line>
<line>Into some realm of undiscovered day? </line>
<line>Our business is with night---'tis come.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>But not </line>
<line>Gone.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Let it roll on---we are ready.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Yes. </line>
<line>Would it were over!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Does the prophet doubt, </line>
<line>To whom the very stars shine Victory?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>I do not doubt of Victory---but the Victor.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>			Well, let thy science settle that. Meantime </line>
<line>I have prepared as many glittering spears </line>
<line>As will out-sparkle our allies---your planets. </line>
<line>There is no more to thwart us. The she-king, </line>
<line>That less than woman, is even now upon </line>
<line>The waters with his female mates. The order </line>
<line>Is issued for the feast in the pavilion. </line>
<line>The first cup which he drains will be the last </line>
<line>Quaffed by the line of Nimrod.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>'Twas a brave one.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>And is a weak one---'tis worn out---we'll mend it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Art sure of that?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Its founder was a hunter--- </line>
<line>I am a soldier---what is there to fear?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>The soldier.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					And the priest, it may be: but </line>
<line>If you thought thus, or think, why not retain </line>
<line>Your king of concubines? why stir me up? </line>
<line>Why spur me to this enterprise? your own </line>
<line>No less than mine?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Look to the sky!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>I look.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>What seest thou?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					A fair summer's twilight, and </line>
<line>The gathering of the stars.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					And midst them, mark </line>
<line>Yon earliest, and the brightest, which so quivers, </line>
<line>As it would quit its place in the blue ether.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Well?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>'Tis thy natal ruler---thy birth planet.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Arb.
</speaker><stage>touching his scabbard</stage>
<line>My star is in this scabbard: when it shines, </line>
<line>It shall out-dazzle comets. Let us think </line>
<line>Of what is to be done to justify </line>
<line>Thy planets and their portents. When we conquer, </line>
<line>They shall have temples---aye, and priests---and thou </line>
<line>Shalt be the pontiff of---what Gods thou wilt; </line>
<line>For I observe that they are ever just, </line>
<line>And own the bravest for the most devout.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Aye, and the most devout for brave---thou hast not </line>
<line>Seen me turn back from battle.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					No; I own thee </line>
<line>As firm in fight as Babylonia's captain, </line>
<line>As skilful in Chaldea's worship: now, </line>
<line>Will it but please thee to forget the priest, </line>
<line>And be the warrior?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Why not both?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>The better; </line>
<line>And yet it almost shames me, we shall have </line>
<line>So little to effect. This woman's warfare </line>
<line>Degrades the very conqueror. To have plucked </line>
<line>A bold and bloody despot from his throne, </line>
<line>And grappled with him, clashing steel with steel, </line>
<line>That were heroic or to win or fall; </line>
<line>But to upraise my sword against this silkworm, </line>
<line>And hear him whine, it may be---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Do not deem it: </line>
<line>He has that in him which may make you strife yet; </line>
<line>And were he all you think, his guards are hardy, </line>
<line>And headed by the cool, stern Salemenes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>They'll not resist.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Why not? they are soldiers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>True, </line>
<line>And therefore need a soldier to command them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>That Salemenes is.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					But not their King. </line>
<line>Besides, he hates the effeminate thing that governs, </line>
<line>For the Queen's sake, his sister. Mark you not </line>
<line>He keeps aloof from all the revels?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>But </line>
<line>Not from the council---there he is ever constant.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>And ever thwarted: what would you have more </line>
<line>To make a rebel out of? A fool reigning, </line>
<line>His blood dishonoured, and himself disdained:</line> 
<line>Why, it is <em>his</em> revenge we work for.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Could </line>
<line>He but be brought to think so: this I doubt of.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>What, if we sound him?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Yes---if the time served.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Balea</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>Satraps! The king commands your presence at </line>
<line>The feast to-night.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>To hear is to obey. </line>
<line>In the pavilion?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>No; here in the palace.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>How! in the palace? it was not thus ordered.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>It is so ordered now.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>And why?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>I know not. </line>
<line>May I retire?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Stay.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Bel.
</speaker><stage>to Arb. aside</stage>
<line>Hush! let him go his way.</line>
<stage>Alternately to Bal.</stage>
<line>Yes, Balea, thank the Monarch, kiss the hem</line> 
<line>Of his imperial robe, and say, his slaves </line>
<line>Will take the crumbs he deigns to scatter from </line>
<line>His royal table at the hour---was't midnight?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>It was: the place, the hall of Nimrod. Lords, </line>
<line>I humble me before you, and depart. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Balea</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>I like not this same sudden change of place; </line>
<line>There is some mystery: wherefore should he change it?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Doth he not change a thousand times a day? </line>
<line>Sloth is of all things the most fanciful--- </line>
<line>And moves more parasangs in its intents </line>
<line>Than generals in their marches, when they seek </line>
<line>To leave their foe at fault.---Why dost thou muse?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>He loved that gay pavilion,---it was ever </line>
<line>His summer dotage.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>And he loved his Queen--- </line>
<line>And thrice a thousand harlotry besides--- </line>
<line>And he has loved all things by turns, except </line>
<line>Wisdom and Glory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Still---I like it not. </line>
<line>If he has changed---why, so must we: the attack </line>
<line>Were easy in the isolated bower, </line>
<line>Beset with drowsy guards and drunken courtiers; </line>
<line>But in the hall of Nimrod---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Is it so? </line>
<line>Methought the haughty soldier feared to mount </line>
<line>A throne too easily---does it disappoint thee </line>
<line>To find there is a slipperier step or two </line>
<line>Than what was counted on?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>When the hour comes, </line>
<line>Thou shalt perceive how far I fear or no. </line>
<line>Thou hast seen my life at stake---and gaily played for: </line>
<line>But here is more upon the die---a kingdom.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>I have foretold already---thou wilt win it: </line>
<line>Then on, and prosper.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					Now were I a soothsayer, </line>
<line>I would have boded so much to myself. </line>
<line>But be the stars obeyed---I cannot quarrel </line>
<line>With them, nor their interpreter. Who's here?</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Satraps!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>My Prince!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Well met---I sought ye both, </line>
<line>But elsewhere than the palace.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Wherefore so?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>'Tis not the hour.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					The hour!---what hour?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Of midnight.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Midnight, my Lord!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					What, are you not invited?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Oh! yes---we had forgotten.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Is it usual </line>
<line>Thus to forget a Sovereign's invitation?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Why---we but now received it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Then why here?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>On duty.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					On what duty?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>On the state's. </line>
<line>We have the privilege to approach the presence; </line>
<line>But found the Monarch absent.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And I too </line>
<line>Am upon duty.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>May we crave its purport?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>To arrest two traitors. Guards! Within there!</line>
</sp><stage>Enter Guards.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker><stage>continuing</stage>
<line>					Satraps, </line>
<line>Your swords.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<stage>delivering his</stage>
<line>					My lord, behold my scimitar.</line></sp>
<sp>Arb.
<stage>drawing his sword.</stage>
<line>Take mine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker><stage>advancing</stage>
<line>I will.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>But in your heart the blade--- </line>
<line>The hilt quits not this hand.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>drawing</stage>
<line>How! dost thou brave me? </line>
<line>Tis well---this saves a trial, and false mercy. </line>
<line>Soldiers, hew down the rebel!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Soldiers! Aye--- </line>
<line><em>Alone you</em> dare not.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Alone! foolish slave--- </line>
<line>What is there in thee that a Prince should shrink from </line>
<line>Of open force? We dread thy treason, not </line>
<line>Thy strength: thy tooth is nought without its venom--- </line>
<line>The serpent's, not the lion's. Cut him down.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Bel.
</speaker><stage>interposing</stage>
<line>Arbaces! Are you mad? Have I not rendered </line>
<line><em>My</em> sword? Then trust like me our Sovereign's justice.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>No---I will sooner trust the stars thou prat'st of, </line>
<line>And this slight arm, and die a king at least </line>
<line>Of my own breath and body---so far that </line>
<line>None else shall chain them.</line>
</sp>
    <sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<stage>to the Guards.</stage>
<line>					 You hear <em>him</em> and <em>me</em>.</line>
<line>Take him not,---kill.</line></sp>
<stage>The Guards attack <strong>Arbaces</strong>, who defends himself valiantly and dexterously till they waver.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Is it even so; and must </line>
<line>I do the hangman's office? Recreants! see </line>
<line>How you should fell a traitor.</line></sp>
<stage><strong>Salemenes</strong> attacks <strong>Arbaces</strong>.</stage><stage>Enter <strong>Sardanapalus</strong> and Train.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Hold your hands--- </line>
<line>Upon your lives, I say. What, deaf or drunken? </line>
<line>My sword! O fool, I wear no sword: here, fellow, </line>
<line>Give me thy weapon. </line></sp>
<stage>To a Guard.</stage>
<stage><strong>Sardanapalus</strong> snatches a sword from one of the soldiers, and rushes between the combatants---they separate.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					In my very palace! </line>
<line>What hinders me from cleaving you in twain, </line>
<line>Audacious brawlers?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Sire, your justice.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Or--- </line>
<line>Your weakness.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>raising the sword</stage>
<line>How?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Strike! so the blow's repeated </line>
<line>Upon yon traitor---whom you spare a moment, </line>
<line>I trust, for torture---I'm content.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What---him! </line>
<line>Who dares assail Arbaces?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Indeed! </line>
<line>Prince, you forget yourself, Upon what warrant?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>showing the signet</stage>
<line>			Thine.</line></sp>
<sp>
    <speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<stage>confused.</stage>
<line>					The King's!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Yes! and let the King confirm it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I parted not from this for such a purpose.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>You parted with it for your safety---I </line>
<line>Employed it for the best. Pronounce in person. </line>
<line>Here I am but your slave---a moment past </line>
<line>I was your representative.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then sheathe </line>
<line>Your swords.</line></sp>
<stage><strong>Arbaces</strong> and <strong>Salemenes</strong> return their swords to the scabbards.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Mine's sheathed: I pray you sheathe <em>not</em> yours:</line>
<line>'Tis the sole sceptre left you now with safety.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>A heavy one; the hilt, too, hurts my hand.</line>
<stage>To a Guard.</stage>
<line>Here, fellow, take thy weapon back. Well, sirs,</line>
<line>What doth this mean?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>The Prince must answer that.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Truth upon my part, treason upon theirs.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Treason---Arbaces! treachery and Beleses! </line>
<line>That were an union I will not believe.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Where is the proof?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					I'll answer that, if once </line>
<line>The king demands your fellow-traitor's sword.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Arb.
</speaker><stage>to Sal.</stage>
<line>A sword which hath been drawn as oft as thine </line>
<line>Against his foes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And now against his brother, </line>
<line>And in an hour or so against himself.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That is not possible: he dared not; no--- </line>
<line>No---I'll not hear of such things. These vain bickerings </line>
<line>Are spawned in courts by base intrigues, and baser </line>
<line>Hirelings, who live by lies on good men's lives. </line>
<line>You must have been deceived, my brother.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					First </line>
<line>Let him deliver up his weapon, and </line>
<line>Proclaim himself your subject by that duty, </line>
<line>And I will answer all.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Why, if I thought so--- </line>
<line>But no, it cannot be: the Mede Arbaces--- </line>
<line>The trusty, rough, true soldier---the best captain </line>
<line>Of all who discipline our nations---No, </line>
<line>I'll not insult him thus, to bid him render </line>
<line>The scimitar to me he never yielded </line>
<line>Unto our enemies. Chief, keep your weapon.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>delivering back the signet</stage>
<line>Monarch, take back your signet.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No, retain it; </line>
<line>But use it with more moderation.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Sire, </line>
<line>I used it for your honour, and restore it </line>
<line>Because I cannot keep it with my own. </line>
<line>Bestow it on Arbaces.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>So I should: </line>
<line>He never asked it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Doubt not, he will have it, </line>
<line>Without that hollow semblance of respect.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>I know not what hath prejudiced the Prince </line>
<line>So strongly 'gainst two subjects, than whom none </line>
<line>Have been more zealous for Assyria's weal.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Peace, factious priest, and faithless soldier! thou </line>
<line>Unit'st in thy own person the worst vices </line>
<line>Of the most dangerous orders of mankind. </line>
<line>Keep thy smooth words and juggling homilies </line>
<line>For those who know thee not. Thy fellow's sin </line>
<line>Is, at the least, a bold one, and not tempered </line>
<line>By the tricks taught thee in Chaldea.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Hear him, </line>
<line>My liege---the son of Belus! he blasphemes </line>
<line>The worship of the land, which bows the knee </line>
<line>Before your fathers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Oh! for that I pray you </line>
<line>Let him have absolution. I dispense with </line>
<line>The worship of dead men; feeling that I </line>
<line>Am mortal, and believing that the race </line>
<line>From whence I sprung are---what I see them---ashes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>King! Do not deem so: they are with the stars, </line>
<line>And---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					You shall join them ere they will rise, </line>
<line>If you preach farther---Why,</line>
<em>this</em>
is rank treason.</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>My lord!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					To school me in the worship of </line>
<line>Assyria's idols! Let him be released--- </line>
<line>Give him his sword.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>My Lord, and King, and Brother, </line>
<line>I pray ye pause.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes, and be sermonised, </line>
<line>And dinned, and deafened with dead men and Baal, </line>
<line>And all Chaldea's starry mysteries.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Monarch! respect them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Oh! for that---I love them; </line>
<line>I love to watch them in the deep blue vault, </line>
<line>And to compare them with my Myrrha's eyes; </line>
<line>I love to see their rays redoubled in </line>
<line>The tremulous silver of Euphrates' wave, </line>
<line>As the light breeze of midnight crisps the broad </line>
<line>And rolling water, sighing through the sedges </line>
<line>Which fringe his banks: but whether they may be </line>
<line>Gods, as some say, or the abodes of Gods, </line>
<line>As others hold, or simply lamps of night, </line>
<line>Worlds---or the lights of Worlds---I know nor care not. </line>
<line>There's something sweet in my uncertainty </line>
<line>I would not change for your Chaldean lore; </line>
<line>Besides, I know of these all clay can know </line>
<line>Of aught above it, or below it---nothing. </line>
<line>I see their brilliancy and feel their beauty--- </line>
<line>When they shine on my grave I shall know neither.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>For</line>
<em>neither</em>
, Sire, say
<em>better</em>
.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I will wait, </line>
<line>If it so please you, Pontiff, for that knowledge. </line>
<line>In the mean time receive your sword, and know </line>
<line>That I prefer your service militant </line>
<line>Unto your ministry---not loving either.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>aside</stage>
<line>His lusts have made him mad. Then must I save him, </line>
<line>Spite of himself.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Please you to hear me, Satraps! </line>
<line>And chiefly thou, my priest, because I doubt thee </line>
<line>More than the soldier; and would doubt thee all </line>
<line>Wert thou not half a warrior: let us part </line>
<line>In peace---I'll not say pardon---which must be </line>
<line>Earned by the guilty; this I'll not pronounce ye, </line>
<line>Although upon this breath of mine depends </line>
<line>Your own; and, deadlier for ye, on my fears. </line>
<line>But fear not---for that I am soft, not fearful--- </line>
<line>And so live on. Were I the thing some think me, </line>
<line>Your heads would now be dripping the last drops </line>
<line>Of their attainted gore from the high gates </line>
<line>Of this our palace, into the dry dust, </line>
<line>Their only portion of the coveted kingdom </line>
<line>They would be crowned to reign o'er---let that pass. </line>
<line>As I have said, I will not <em>deem</em> ye guilty,</line>
<line>Nor <em>doom</em> ye guiltless. Albeit better men</line>
<line>Than ye or I stand ready to arraign you; </line>
<line>And should I leave your fate to sterner judges, </line>
<line>And proofs of all kinds, I might sacrifice </line>
<line>Two men, who, whatsoe'er they now are, were </line>
<line>Once honest. Ye are free, sirs.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Sire, this clemency---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Bel.
</speaker><stage>interrupting him</stage>
<line>Is worthy of yourself; and, although innocent, </line>
<line>We thank---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Priest! keep your thanksgivings for Belus; </line>
<line>His offspring needs none.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>But being innocent---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Be silent.---Guilt is loud. If ye are loyal, </line>
<line>Ye are injured men, and should be sad, not grateful.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>So we should be, were justice always done </line>
<line>By earthly power omnipotent; but Innocence </line>
<line>Must oft receive her right as a mere favour.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That's a good sentence for a homily, </line>
<line>Though not for this occasion. Prithee keep it </line>
<line>To plead thy Sovereign's cause before his people.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>I trust there is no cause.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No</line>
<em>cause</em>
, perhaps;
<line>But many causers:---if ye meet with such </line>
<line>In the exercise of your inquisitive function </line>
<line>On earth, or should you read of it in heaven </line>
<line>In some mysterious twinkle of the stars, </line>
<line>Which are your chronicles, I pray you note, </line>
<line>That there are worse things betwixt earth and heaven </line>
<line>Than him who ruleth many and slays none; </line>
<line>And, hating not himself, yet loves his fellows </line>
<line>Enough to spare even those who would not spare him </line>
<line>Were they once masters---but that's doubtful. Satraps! </line>
<line>Your swords and persons are at liberty </line>
<line>To use them as ye will---but from this hour </line>
<line>I have no call for either. Salemenes! </line>
<line>Follow me.</line></sp>
<stage>Exeunt <strong>Sardanapalus, Salemenes</strong>, and the Train, etc., leaving <strong>Arbaces</strong> and <strong>Beleses</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					Beleses!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Now, what think you?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>That we are lost.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					That we have won the kingdom.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>What? thus suspected---with the sword slung o'er us </line>
<line>But by a single hair, and that still wavering, </line>
<line>To be blown down by his imperious breath </line>
<line>Which spared us---why, I know not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Seek not why; </line>
<line>But let us profit by the interval. </line>
<line>The hour is still our own---our power the same--- </line>
<line>The night the same we destined. He hath changed </line>
<line>Nothing except our ignorance of all </line>
<line>Suspicion into such a certainty </line>
<line>As must make madness of delay.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>And yet---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>What, doubting still?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					He spared our lives, nay, more, </line>
<line>Saved them from Salemenes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>And how long </line>
<line>Will he so spare? till the first drunken minute.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Or sober, rather. Yet he did it nobly; </line>
<line>Gave royally what we had forfeited </line>
<line>Basely---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Say bravely.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Somewhat of both, perhaps--- </line>
<line>But it has touched me, and, whate'er betide, </line>
<line>I will no further on.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>And lose the world!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Lose any thing except my own esteem.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>I blush that we should owe our lives to such </line>
<line>A king of distaffs!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>But no less we owe them; </line>
<line>And I should blush far more to take the grantor's!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Thou may'st endure whate'er thou wilt---the stars </line>
<line>Have written otherwise.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					Though they came down, </line>
<line>And marshalled me the way in all their brightness, </line>
<line>I would not follow.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>This is weakness---worse </line>
<line>Than a scared beldam's dreaming of the dead, </line>
<line>And waking in the dark.---Go to---go to.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Methought he looked like Nimrod as he spoke, </line>
<line>Even as the proud imperial statue stands </line>
<line>Looking the monarch of the kings around it, </line>
<line>And sways, while they but ornament, the temple.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>I told you that you had too much despised him, </line>
<line>And that there was some royalty within him--- </line>
<line>What then? he is the nobler foe.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>But we </line>
<line>The meaner.---Would he had not spared us!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>So--- </line>
<line>Wouldst thou be sacrificed thus readily?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>No---but it had been better to have died </line>
<line>Than live ungrateful.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Oh, the souls of some men! </line>
<line>Thou wouldst digest what some call treason, and </line>
<line>Fools treachery---and, behold, upon the sudden, </line>
<line>Because for something or for nothing, this </line>
<line>Rash reveller steps, ostentatiously, </line>
<line>'Twixt thee and Salemenes, thou art turned </line>
<line>Into---what shall I say?---Sardanapalus! </line>
<line>I know no name more ignominious.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>But </line>
<line>An hour ago, who dared to term me such </line>
<line>Had held his life but lightly---as it is, </line>
<line>I must forgive you, even as he forgave us--- </line>
<line>Semiramis herself would not have done it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>No---the Queen liked no sharers of the kingdom, </line>
<line>Not even a husband.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					I must serve him truly---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>And humbly?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					No, sir, proudly---being honest. </line>
<line>I shall be nearer thrones than you to heaven; </line>
<line>And if not quite so haughty, yet more lofty. </line>
<line>You may do your own deeming---you have codes, </line>
<line>And mysteries, and corollaries of </line>
<line>Right and wrong, which I lack for my direction, </line>
<line>And must pursue but what a plain heart teaches. </line>
<line>And now you know me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Have you finished?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Yes--- </line>
<line>With you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>And would, perhaps, betray as well </line>
<line>As quit me?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>That's a sacerdotal thought, </line>
<line>And not a soldier's.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Be it what you will--- </line>
<line>Truce with these wranglings, and but hear me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					No--- </line>
<line>There is more peril in your subtle spirit </line>
<line>Than in a phalanx.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>If it must be so--- </line>
<line>I'll on alone.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Alone!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Thrones hold but one.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>But this is filled.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					With worse than vacancy--- </line>
<line>A despised monarch. Look to it, Arbaces: </line>
<line>I have still aided, cherished, loved, and urged you; </line>
<line>Was willing even to serve you, in the hope </line>
<line>To serve and save Assyria. Heaven itself </line>
<line>Seemed to consent, and all events were friendly, </line>
<line>Even to the last, till that your spirit shrunk </line>
<line>Into a shallow softness; but now, rather </line>
<line>Than see my country languish, I will be </line>
<line>Her saviour or the victim of her tyrant--- </line>
<line>Or one or both---for sometimes both are one; </line>
<line>And if I win---Arbaces is my servant.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker><em>Your</em>
servant!
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Why not? better than be slave,</line> 
<line>The <em>pardoned</em> slave of <em>she</em> Sardanapalus!</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Pania</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>			My Lords, I bear an order from the king.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>It is obeyed ere spoken.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Notwithstanding, </line>
<line>Let's hear it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Forthwith, on this very night, </line>
<line>Repair to your respective satrapies </line>
<line>Of Babylon and Media.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>With our troops?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>My order is unto the Satraps and </line>
<line>Their household train.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					But---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>It must be obeyed: </line>
<line>Say, we depart.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>My order is to see you </line>
<line>Depart, and not to bear your answer.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Bel.
</speaker><stage>aside</stage>
<line>Aye! </line>
<line>Well, Sir---we will accompany you hence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>I will retire to marshal forth the guard </line>
<line>Of honour which befits your rank, and wait </line>
<line>Your leisure, so that it the hour exceeds not.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Pania</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Now then obey!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Doubtless.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Yes, to the gates </line>
<line>That grate the palace, which is now our prison--- </line>
<line>No further.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					Thou hast harped the truth indeed! </line>
<line>The realm itself, in all its wide extension, </line>
<line>Yawns. dungeons at each step for thee and me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Graves!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>If I thought so, this good sword should dig </line>
<line>One more than mine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>It shall have work enough. </line>
<line>Let me hope better than thou augurest; </line>
<line>At present, let us hence as best we may. </line>
<line>Thou dost agree with me in understanding </line>
<line>This order as a sentence?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Why, what other </line>
<line>Interpretation should it bear? it is </line>
<line>The very policy of Orient monarchs--- </line>
<line>Pardon and poison---favours and a sword--- </line>
<line>A distant voyage, and an eternal sleep. </line>
<line>How many Satraps in his father's time---</line> 
<line>For he I own is, or at least <em>was</em>, bloodless---</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>But</line>
<em>will</em>
not---
<em>can</em>
not be so now.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					I doubt it. </line>
<line>How many Satraps have I seen set out </line>
<line>In his Sire's day for mighty Vice-royalties, </line>
<line>Whose tombs are on their path! I know not how, </line>
<line>But they all sickened by the way, it was </line>
<line>So long and heavy.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					Let us but regain </line>
<line>The free air of the city, and we'll shorten </line>
<line>The journey.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>					'Twill be shortened at the gates, </line>
<line>It may be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>No; they hardly will risk that. </line>
<line>They mean us to die privately, but not </line>
<line>Within the palace or the city walls, </line>
<line>Where we are known, and may have partisans: </line>
<line>If they had meant to slay us here, we were </line>
<line>No longer with the living. Let us hence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>If I but thought he did not mean my life---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Fool! hence---what else should despotism alarmed </line>
<line>Mean? Let us but rejoin our troops, and march.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Towards our provinces?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>					No; towards your kingdom. </line>
<line>There's time---there's heart, and hope, and power, and means--- </line>
<line>Which their half measures leave us in full scope.--- </line>
<line>Away!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>And I even yet repenting must </line>
<line>Relapse to guilt!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Self-defence is a virtue, </line>
<line>Sole bulwark of all right. Away, I say! </line>
<line>Let's leave this place, the air grows thick and choking, </line>
<line>And the walls have a scent of night-shade---hence! </line>
<line>Let us not leave them time for further council. </line>
<line>Our quick departure proves our civic zeal; </line>
<line>Our quick departure hinders our good escort, </line>
<line>The worthy Pania, from anticipating </line>
<line>The orders of some parasangs from hence: </line>
<line>Nay, there's no other choice, but --- hence, I say.</line></sp>
<stage>Exit with <strong>Arbaces</strong>, who follows reluctantly.</stage>
<stage>Enter <strong>Sardanapalus</strong> and <strong>Salemenes</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Well, all is remedied, and without bloodshed, </line>
<line>That worst of mockeries of a remedy; </line>
<line>We are now secure by these men's exile.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Yes, </line>
<line>As he who treads on flowers is from the adder </line>
<line>Twined round their roots.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Why, what wouldst have me do?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Undo what you have done.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Revoke my pardon?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Replace the crown now tottering on your temples.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That were tyrannical.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>But sure.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>We are so. </line>
<line>What danger can they work upon the frontier?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>They are not there yet---never should they be so, </line>
<line>Were I well listened to.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
Nay, I
<em>have</em>
listened
<line>Impartially to thee---why not to them?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>You may know that hereafter; as it is, </line>
<line>I take my leave to order forth the guard.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And you will join us at the banquet?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Sire, </line>
<line>Dispense with me---I am no wassailer: </line>
<line>Command me in all service save the Bacchant's.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Nay, but 'tis fit to revel now and then.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And fit that some should watch for those who revel </line>
<line>Too oft. Am I permitted to depart?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes---Stay a moment, my good Salemenes, </line>
<line>My brother---my best subject---better Prince </line>
<line>Than I am King. You should have been the monarch, </line>
<line>And I---I know not what, and care not; but </line>
<line>Think not I am insensible to all </line>
<line>Thine honest wisdom, and thy rough yet kind, </line>
<line>Though oft-reproving sufferance of my follies. </line>
<line>If I have spared these men against thy counsel, </line>
<line>That is, their lives---it is not that I doubt </line>
<line>The advice was sound; but, let them live: we will not </line>
<line>Cavil about their lives---so let them mend them. </line>
<line>Their banishment will leave me still sound sleep, </line>
<line>Which their death had not left me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Thus you run </line>
<line>The risk to sleep for ever, to save traitors--- </line>
<line>A moment's pang now changed for years of crime. </line>
<line>Still let them be made quiet.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Tempt me not; </line>
<line>My word is past.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					But it may be recalled.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Tis royal.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					And should therefore be decisive. </line>
<line>This half-indulgence of an exile serves </line>
<line>But to provoke---a pardon should be full, </line>
<line>Or it is none.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And who persuaded me </line>
<line>After I had repealed them, or at least </line>
<line>Only dismissed them from our presence, who </line>
<line>Urged me to send them to their satrapies?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>True; that I had forgotten; that is, Sire, </line>
<line>If they e'er reached their Satrapies---why, then, </line>
<line>Reprove me more for my advice.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And if </line>
<line>They do not reach them---look to it!---in safety, </line>
<line>In safety, mark me---and security--- </line>
<line>Look to thine own.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Permit me to depart;</line> 
<line>Their <em>safety</em> shall be cared for.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Get thee hence, then; </line>
<line>And, prithee, think more gently of thy brother.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Sire, I shall ever duly serve my sovereign.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>solus</stage><line>That man is of a temper too severe; </line>
<line>Hard but as lofty as the rock, and free </line>
<line>From all the taints of common earth---while I </line>
<line>Am softer clay, impregnated with flowers: </line>
<line>But as our mould is, must the produce be. </line>
<line>If I have erred this time, 'tis on the side </line>
<line>Where Error sits most lightly on that sense, </line>
<line>I know not what to call it; but it reckons </line>
<line>With me ofttimes for pain, and sometimes pleasure; </line>
<line>A spirit which seems placed about my heart </line>
<line>To count its throbs, not quicken them, and ask </line>
<line>Questions which mortal never dared to ask me, </line>
<line>Nor Baal, though an oracular deity--- </line>
<line>Albeit his marble face majestical </line>
<line>Frowns as the shadows of the evening dim </line>
<line>His brows to changed expression, till at times </line>
<line>I think the statue looks in act to speak. </line>
<line>Away with these vain thoughts, I will be joyous--- </line>
<line>And here comes Joy's true herald.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Myrrha</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					King! the sky </line>
<line>Is overcast, and musters muttering thunder, </line>
<line>In clouds that seem approaching fast, and show </line>
<line>In forkéd flashes a commanding tempest. </line>
<line>Will you then quit the palace?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Tempest, say'st thou?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Aye, my good lord.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					For my own part, I should be </line>
<line>Not ill content to vary the smooth scene, </line>
<line>And watch the warring elements; but this </line>
<line>Would little suit the silken garments and </line>
<line>Smooth faces of our festive friends. Say, Myrrha, </line>
<line>Art thou of those who dread the roar of clouds?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>In my own country we respect their voices </line>
<line>As auguries of Jove.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Jove!---aye, your Baal--- </line>
<line>Ours also has a property in thunder, </line>
<line>And ever and anon some falling bolt </line>
<line>Proves his divinity,---and yet sometimes </line>
<line>Strikes his own altars.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>That were a dread omen.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes---for the priests. Well, we will not go forth </line>
<line>Beyond the palace walls to-night, but make </line>
<line>Our feast within.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Now, Jove be praised! that he </line>
<line>Hath heard the prayer thou wouldst not hear. The Gods </line>
<line>Are kinder to thee than thou to thyself, </line>
<line>And flash this storm between thee and thy foes, </line>
<line>To shield thee from them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Child, if there be peril, </line>
<line>Methinks it is the same within these walls </line>
<line>As on the river's brink.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Not so; these walls </line>
<line>Are high and strong, and guarded. Treason has </line>
<line>To penetrate through many a winding way, </line>
<line>And massy portal; but in the pavilion </line>
<line>There is no bulwark.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					No, nor in the palace, </line>
<line>Nor in the fortress, nor upon the top </line>
<line>Of cloud-fenced Caucasus, where the eagle sits </line>
<line>Nested in pathless clefts, if treachery be: </line>
<line>Even as the arrow finds the airy king, </line>
<line>The steel will reach the earthly. But be calm; </line>
<line>The men, or innocent or guilty, are </line>
<line>Banished, and far upon their way.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>They live, then?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>So sanguinary?</line>
<em>Thou!</em>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					I would not shrink </line>
<line>From just infliction of due punishment </line>
<line>On those who seek your life: were't otherwise, </line>
<line>I should not merit mine. Besides, you heard </line>
<line>The princely Salemenes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>This is strange; </line>
<line>The gentle and the austere are both against me, </line>
<line>And urge me to revenge.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>'Tis a Greek virtue.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>But not a kingly one---I'll none on't; or </line>
<line>If ever I indulge in't, it shall be </line>
<line>With kings---my equals.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					These men sought to be so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Myrrha, this is too feminine, and springs </line>
<line>From fear---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					For you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No matter, still 'tis fear. </line>
<line>I have observed your sex, once roused to wrath, </line>
<line>Are timidly vindictive to a pitch </line>
<line>Of perseverance, which I would not copy. </line>
<line>I thought you were exempt from this, as from </line>
<line>The childish helplessness of Asian women.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>My Lord, I am no boaster of my love, </line>
<line>Nor of my attributes; I have shared your splendour, </line>
<line>And will partake your fortunes. You may live </line>
<line>To find one slave more true than subject myriads: </line>
<line>But this the Gods avert! I am content </line>
<line>To be beloved on trust for what I feel, </line>
<line>Rather than prove it to you in your griefs, </line>
<line>Which might not yield to any cares of mine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Grief cannot come where perfect love exists, </line>
<line>Except to heighten it, and vanish from </line>
<line>That which it could not scare away. Let's in--- </line>
<line>The hour approaches, and we must prepare </line>
<line>To meet the invited guests who grace our feast.</line></sp>
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
</div>
</div><div type="act"><head>ACT III.</head>
<div type="scene"><head>Scene I.</head>
<stage>---The Hall of the Palace illuminated---<strong>Sardanapalus</strong> and his Guests at Table.---A storm without, and Thunder occasionally heard during the Banquet.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Fill full! why this is as it should be: here </line>
<line>Is my true realm, amidst bright eyes and faces </line>
<line>Happy as fair! Here sorrow cannot reach.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zam.</speaker>
<line>Nor elsewhere---where the King is, pleasure sparkles.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Is not this better now than Nimrod's huntings, </line>
<line>Or my wild Grandam's chase in search of kingdoms </line>
<line>She could not keep when conquered?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>Mighty though </line>
<line>They were, as all thy royal line have been, </line>
<line>Yet none of those who went before have reached </line>
<line>The acmé of Sardanapalus, who </line>
<line>Has placed his joy in peace---the sole true glory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And pleasure, good Altada, to which glory </line>
<line>Is but the path. What is it that we seek? </line>
<line>Enjoyment! We have cut the way short to it, </line>
<line>And not gone tracking it through human ashes, </line>
<line>Making a grave with every footstep.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zam.</speaker>
<line>					No; </line>
<line>All hearts are happy, and all voices bless </line>
<line>The King of peace---who holds a world in jubilee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Art sure of that? I have heard otherwise; </line>
<line>Some say that there be traitors.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zam.</speaker>
<line>					Traitors they </line>
<line>Who dare to say so!---'Tis impossible. </line>
<line>What cause?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What cause? true,---fill the goblet up; </line>
<line>We will not think of them: there are none such, </line>
<line>Or if there be, they are gone.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					Guests, to my pledge! </line>
<line>Down on your knees, and drink a measure to </line>
<line>The safety of the King---the monarch, say I? </line>
    <line>The God Sardanapalus!</line>
<stage><strong>Zames</strong> and the Guests kneel, and exclaim---</stage>
<line>					Mightier than</line> 
<line>His father Baal, the God Sardanapalus!</line></sp>
<stage>It thunders as they kneel; some start up in confusion.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Zam.</speaker>
<line>Why do you rise, my friends? in that strong peal </line>
<line>His father gods consented.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Menaced, rather. </line>
<line>King, wilt thou bear this mad impiety?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Impiety!---nay, if the sires who reigned </line>
<line>Before me can be Gods, I'll not disgrace </line>
<line>Their lineage. But arise, my pious friends; </line>
<line>Hoard your devotion for the Thunderer there: </line>
<line>I seek but to be loved, not worshipped.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					Both--- </line>
<line>Both you must ever be by all true subjects.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Methinks the thunders still increase: it is </line>
<line>An awful night.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Oh yes, for those who have </line>
<line>No palace to protect their worshippers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>			That's true, my Myrrha; and could I convert </line>
<line>My realm to one wide shelter for the wretched, </line>
<line>I'd do it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Thou'rt no God, then---not to be </line>
<line>Able to work a will so good and general, </line>
<line>As thy wish would imply.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And your Gods, then, </line>
<line>Who can, and do not?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Do not speak of that, </line>
<line>Lest we provoke them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>True---, they love not censure </line>
<line>Better than mortals. Friends, a thought has struck me: </line>
<line>Were there no temples, would there, think ye, be </line>
<line>Air worshippers? that is, when it is angry, </line>
<line>And pelting as even now.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>The Persian prays </line>
<line>Upon his mountain.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes, when the Sun shines.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And I would ask if this your palace were </line>
<line>Unroofed and desolate, how many flatterers </line>
<line>Would lick the dust in which the King lay low?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>The fair Ionian is too sarcastic </line>
<line>Upon a nation whom she knows not well; </line>
<line>The Assyrians know no pleasure but their King's, </line>
<line>And homage is their pride.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Nay, pardon, guests, </line>
<line>The fair Greek's readiness of speech.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
<em>Pardon!</em>
sire:
<line>We honour her of all things next to thee. </line>
<line>Hark! what was that?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zam.</speaker>
<line>That! nothing but the jar </line>
<line>Of distant portals shaken by the wind.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>It sounded like the clash of---hark again!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zam.</speaker>
<line>The big rain pattering on the roof.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No more. </line>
<line>Myrrha, my love, hast thou thy shell in order? </line>
<line>Sing me a song of Sappho; her, thou know'st, </line>
<line>Who in thy country threw---</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Pania</strong>, with his sword and garments bloody, and disordered. The guests rise in confusion.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker><stage>to the Guards</stage>
<line>					Look to the portals; </line>
<line>And with your best speed to the walls without. </line>
<line>Your arms! To arms! The King's in danger. Monarch </line>
<line>Excuse this haste,---'tis faith.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Speak on.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>It is </line>
<line>As Salemenes feared; the faithless Satraps---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>You are wounded---give some wine. Take breath, good Pania.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>'Tis nothing---a mere flesh wound. I am worn </line>
<line>More with my speed to warn my sovereign, </line>
<line>Than hurt in his defence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Well, Sir, the rebels?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>			Soon as Arbaces and Beleses reached </line>
<line>Their stations in the city, they refused </line>
<line>To march; and on my attempt to use the power </line>
<line>Which I was delegated with, they called </line>
<line>Upon their troops, who rose in fierce defiance.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>All?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Too many.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Spare not of thy free speech, </line>
<line>To spare mine ears---the truth.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>My own slight guard </line>
<line>Were faithful, and what's left of it is still so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And are these all the force still faithful?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					No--- </line>
<line>The Bactrians, now led on by Salemenes, </line>
<line>Who even then was on his way, still urged </line>
<line>By strong suspicion of the Median chiefs, </line>
<line>Are numerous, and make strong head against </line>
<line>The rebels, fighting inch by inch, and forming </line>
<line>An orb around the palace, where they mean </line>
<line>To centre all their force, and save the King.</line>
    <stage>He hesitates.</stage>
<line>I am charged to---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>'Tis no time for hesitation.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Prince Salemenes doth implore the King </line>
<line>To arm himself, although but for a moment, </line>
<line>And show himself unto the soldiers: his </line>
<line>Sole presence in this instant might do more </line>
<line>Than hosts can do in his behalf.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					What, ho! </line>
<line>My armour there.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And wilt thou?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Will I not? </line>
<line>Ho, there!---but seek not for the buckler: 'tis </line>
<line>Too heavy:---a light cuirass and my sword. </line>
<line>Where are the rebels?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Scarce a furlong's length </line>
<line>From the outward wall the fiercest conflict rages.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then I may charge on horseback. Sfero, ho! </line>
<line>Order my horse out.---There is space enough </line>
<line>Even in our courts, and by the outer gate, </line>
<line>To marshal half the horsemen of Arabia.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Sfero</strong> for the armour.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>How I do love thee!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I ne'er doubted it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>But now I know thee.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<stage>to his Attendant.</stage>
<line>					Bring down my spear too---</line> 
<line>Where's Salemenes?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					Where a soldier should be, </line>
<line>In the thick of the fight.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then hasten to him---Is </line>
<line>The path still open, and communication </line>
<line>Left 'twixt the palace and the phalanx?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					'Twas </line>
<line>When I late left him, and I have no fear; </line>
<line>Our troops were steady, and the phalanx formed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Tell him to spare his person for the present, </line>
<line>And that I will not spare my own---and say, </line>
<line>I come.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>There's victory in the very word. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Pania</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Altada---Zames---forth, and arm ye! There </line>
<line>Is all in readiness in the armoury. </line>
<line>See that the women are bestowed in safety </line>
<line>In the remote apartments: let a guard </line>
<line>Be set before them, with strict charge to quit </line>
<line>The post but with their lives---command it, Zames. </line>
<line>Altada, arm yourself, and return here; </line>
<line>Your post is near our person.</line></sp>
<stage>Exeunt <strong>Zames, Altada</strong>, and all save <strong>Myrrha</strong></stage>
    <stage>Enter <strong>Sfero</strong> and others with the King's Arms, etc.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>					King! your armour.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker><stage>arming himself</stage>
<line>Give me the cuirass---so: my baldric; now </line>
<line>My sword: I had forgot the helm---where is it? </line>
<line>That's well---no, 'tis too heavy; you mistake, too--- </line>
<line>It was not this I meant, but that which bears </line>
<line>A diadem around it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>Sire, I deemed </line>
<line>That too conspicuous from the precious stones </line>
<line>To risk your sacred brow beneath---and trust me, </line>
<line>This is of better metal, though less rich.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>			You deemed! Are you too turned a rebel? Fellow! </line>
<line>Your part is to obey: return, and---no--- </line>
<line>It is too late---I will go forth without it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>At least, wear this.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Wear Caucasus! why, 'tis </line>
<line>A mountain on my temples.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>Sire, the meanest </line>
<line>Soldier goes not forth thus exposed to battle. </line>
<line>All men will recognise you---for the storm </line>
<line>Has ceased, and the moon breaks forth in her brightness.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I go forth to be recognised, and thus </line>
<line>Shall be so sooner. Now---my spear! I'm armed. </line>
<stage>In going stops short, and turns to <strong>Sfero</strong></stage>
<line>Sfero---I had forgotten---bring the mirror.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>The mirror, Sire?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Yes, sir, of polished brass, </line>
<line>Brought from the spoils of India---but be speedy.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Sfero</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Myrrha, retire unto a place of safety. </line>
<line>Why went you not forth with the other damsels?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Because my place is here.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And when I am gone---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I follow.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
<em>You!</em>
to battle?</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>If it were so, </line>
<line>'Twere not the first Greek girl had trod the path.</line> 
<line>I will await here your <em>return</em>.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					The place </line>
<line>Is spacious, and the first to be sought out, </line>
<line>If they prevail; and, if it be so, </line>
<line>And I return not---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Still we meet again.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>How?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					In the spot where all must meet at last--- </line>
<line>In Hades! if there be, as I believe, </line>
<line>A shore beyond the Styx; and if there be not, </line>
<line>In ashes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Darest thou so much?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I dare all things </line>
<line>Except survive what I have loved, to be </line>
<line>A rebel's booty: forth, and do your bravest.</line></sp>
    <stage>Re-enter <strong>Sfero</strong> with the mirror.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker><stage>looking at himself</stage><line>This cuirass fits me well, the baldric better, </line>
<line>And the helm not at all. Methinks I seem </line>
<stage>Flings away the helmet after trying it again.</stage>
<line>Passing well in these toys; and now to prove them. </line>
<line>Altada! Where's Altada?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>Waiting, Sire, </line>
<line>Without: he has your shield in readiness.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>True---I forgot---he is my shield-bearer </line>
<line>By right of blood, derived from age to age. </line>
<line>Myrrha, embrace me;---yet once more---once more--- </line>
<line>Love me, whate'er betide. My chiefest glory </line>
<line>Shall be to make me worthier of your love.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>			Go forth, and conquer!</line>
<stage>Exeunt <strong>Sardanapalus</strong> and <strong>Sfero</strong>.</stage>
<line>					Now, I am alone:</line> 
<line>All are gone forth, and of that all how few </line>
<line>Perhaps return! Let him but vanquish, and </line>
<line>Me perish! If he vanquish not, I perish; </line>
<line>For I will not outlive him. He has wound </line>
<line>About my heart, I know not how nor why. </line>
<line>Not for that he is King; for now his kingdom </line>
<line>Rocks underneath his throne, and the earth yawns </line>
<line>To yield him no more of it than a grave; </line>
<line>And yet I love him more. Oh, mighty Jove! </line>
<line>Forgive this monstrous love for a barbarian, </line>
<line>Who knows not of Olympus! yes, I love him </line>
<line>Now---now---far more than---Hark---to the war shout! </line>
<line>Methinks it nears me. If it should be so,</line>
<stage>She draws forth a small vial.</stage>
<line>This cunning Colchian poison, which my father </line>
<line>Learned to compound on Euxine shores, and taught me </line>
<line>How to preserve, shall free me! It had freed me </line>
<line>Long ere this hour, but that I loved, until </line>
<line>I half forgot I was a slave:---where all </line>
<line>Are slaves save One, and proud of servitude, </line>
<line>So they are served in turn by something lower </line>
<line>In the degree of bondage: we forget </line>
<line>That shackles worn like ornaments no less </line>
<line>Are chains. Again that shout! and now the clash </line>
<line>Of arms---and now---and now---</line></sp>
    <stage>Enter <strong>Altada</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					Ho, Sfero, ho!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>He is not here; what wouldst thou with him? How </line>
<line>Goes on the conflict?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					Dubiously and fiercely.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And the King?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					Like a king. I must find Sfero, </line>
<line>And bring him a new spear with his own helmet. </line>
<line>He fights till now bare-headed, and by far </line>
<line>Too much exposed. The soldiers knew his face, </line>
<line>And the foe too; and in the moon's broad light, </line>
<line>His silk tiara and his flowing hair </line>
<line>Make him a mark too royal. Every arrow </line>
<line>Is pointed at the fair hair and fair features, </line>
<line>And the broad fillet which crowns both.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Ye Gods, </line>
<line>Who fulminate o'er my father's land, protect him! </line>
<line>Were you sent by the King?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>By Salemenes, </line>
<line>Who sent me privily upon this charge, </line>
<line>Without the knowledge of the careless sovereign. </line>
<line>The King! the King fights as he revels! ho! </line>
<line>What, Sfero! I will seek the armoury--- </line>
<line>He must be there. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Altada</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis no dishonour---no--- </line>
<line>'Tis no dishonour to have loved this man. </line>
<line>I almost wish now, what I never wished </line>
<line>Before---that he were Grecian. If Alcides </line>
<line>Were shamed in wearing Lydian Omphale's </line>
<line>She-garb, and wielding her vile distaff; surely </line>
<line>He, who springs up a Hercules at once, </line>
<line>Nursed in effeminate arts from youth to manhood, </line>
<line>And rushes from the banquet to the battle, </line>
<line>As though it were a bed of love, deserves </line>
<line>That a Greek girl should be his paramour, </line>
<line>And a Greek bard his minstrel---a Greek tomb </line>
<line>His monument. How goes the strife, sir?</line></sp>
<stage><em>Enter an Officer.</em></stage>
<sp><speaker>Officer.</speaker>
<line>					Lost, </line>
<line>Lost almost past recovery. Zames! Where </line>
<line>Is Zames?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Posted with the guard appointed </line>
<line>To watch before the apartment of the women.</line>
<stage>Exit Officer.</stage></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker><stage>sola</stage>
<line>He's gone; and told no more than that all's lost! </line>
<line>What need have I to know more? In those words, </line>
<line>Those little words, a kingdom and a king, </line>
<line>A line of thirteen ages, and the lives </line>
<line>Of thousands, and the fortune of all left </line>
<line>With life, are merged; and I, too, with the great, </line>
<line>Like a small bubble breaking with the wave </line>
<line>Which bore it, shall be nothing. At the least, </line>
<line>My fate is in my keeping: no proud victor </line>
<line>Shall count me with his spoils.</line></sp>
    <stage>Enter <strong>Pania</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					Away with me, </line>
<line>Myrrha, without delay; we must not lose </line>
<line>A moment---all that's left us now.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>The King?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Sent me here to conduct you hence, beyond </line>
<line>The river, by a secret passage.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Then </line>
<line>He lives---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>And charged me to secure your life, </line>
<line>And beg you to live on for his sake, till </line>
<line>He can rejoin you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Will he then give way?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Not till the last. Still, still he does whate'er </line>
<line>Despair can do; and step by step disputes </line>
<line>The very palace.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					They are here, then:---aye, </line>
<line>Their shouts come ringing through the ancient halls, </line>
<line>Never profaned by rebel echoes till </line>
<line>This fatal night. Farewell, Assyria's line! </line>
<line>Farewell to all of Nimrod! Even the name </line>
<line>Is now no more.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Away with me---away!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>No: I'll die here!---Away, and tell your King </line>
<line>I loved him to the last.</line></sp>
    <stage>Enter <strong>Sardanapalus</strong> and <strong>Salemenes</strong> with Soldiers. <strong>Pania</strong> quits <strong>Myrrha</strong>, and ranges himself with them.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Since it is thus, </line>
<line>We'll die where we were born---in our own halls. </line>
<line>Serry your ranks---stand firm. I have despatched </line>
<line>A trusty satrap for the guard of Zames, </line>
<line>All fresh and faithful; they'll be here anon. </line>
<line>All is not over.---Pania, look to Myrrha.</line></sp>
<stage><strong>Pania</strong> returns towards <strong>Myrrha.</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>We have breathing time; yet once more charge, my friends--- </line>
<line>One for Assyria!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Rather say for Bactria! </line>
<line>My faithful Bactrians, I will henceforth be </line>
<line>King of your nation, and we'll hold together </line>
<line>This realm as province.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Hark! they come---they come.</line></sp>
    <stage>Enter <strong>Beleses</strong> and <strong>Arbaces</strong> with the Rebels.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Arb.</speaker>
<line>Set on, we have them in the toil. Charge! charge!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>On! on!---Heaven fights for us, and with us---On!</line>
<stage>They charge the King and
<strong>Salemenes</strong>
with their troops, who defend themselves till the arrival of
<strong>Zames</strong>
with the Guard before mentioned. The Rebels are then driven off, and pursued by
<strong>Salemenes</strong>, etc. As the King is going to join the pursuit, <strong>Beleses</strong> crosses him.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
    <line>Ho! tyrant---<em>I</em> will end this war.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Even so, </line>
<line>My warlike priest, and precious prophet, and </line>
<line>Grateful and trusty subject: yield, I pray thee. </line>
<line>I would reserve thee for a fitter doom, </line>
<line>Rather than dip my hands in holy blood.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>Thine hour is come.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					No, thine.---I've lately read, </line>
<line>Though but a young astrologer, the stars; </line>
<line>And ranging round the zodiac, found thy fate </line>
<line>In the sign of the Scorpion, which proclaims </line>
<line>That thou wilt now be crushed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bel.</speaker>
<line>But not by thee.</line></sp>
<stage>				They fight;
<strong>Beleses</strong>
is wounded and disarmed.</stage>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<stage>raising his sword to despatch him, exclaims</stage><line>---Now call upon thy planets, will they shoot </line>
<line>From the sky to preserve their seer and credit? </line>
<stage>A party of Rebels enter and rescue <strong>Beleses</strong>. They assail the King, who in turn, is rescued by a Party of his Soldiers, who drive the Rebels off.</stage>
<line>The villain was a prophet after all. </line>
<line>Upon them---ho! there---victory is ours.</line></sp>
<stage>Exit in pursuit.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Myr.
</speaker><stage>to Pan.</stage><line>Pursue! Why stand'st thou here, and leavest the ranks </line>
<line>Of fellow-soldiers conquering without thee?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>The King's command was not to quit thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
<em>Me!</em>
<line>Think not of me---a single soldier's arm </line>
<line>Must not be wanting now. I ask no guard, </line>
<line>I need no guard: what, with a world at stake, </line>
<line>Keep watch upon a woman? Hence, I say, </line>
<line>Or thou art shamed! Nay, then, <em>I</em> will go forth,</line>
<line>A feeble female, 'midst their desperate strife,</line> 
<line>And bid thee guard me <em>there</em>---where thou shouldst shield</line>
<line>Thy sovereign. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Myrrha</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					Yet stay, damsel!---She's gone. </line>
<line>If aught of ill betide her, better I </line>
<line>Had lost my life. Sardanapalus holds her </line>
<line>Far dearer than his kingdom, yet he fights </line>
<line>For that too; and can I do less than he, </line>
<line>Who never flashed a scimitar till now? </line>
<line>Myrrha, return, and I obey you, though </line>
<line>In disobedience to the monarch. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit
<strong>Pania</strong> Enter <strong>Altada</strong> and <strong>Sfero</strong> by an opposite door.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					Myrrha! </line>
<line>What, gone? yet she was here when the fight raged, </line>
<line>And Pania also. Can aught have befallen them?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>I saw both safe, when late the rebels fled; </line>
<line>They probably are but retired to make </line>
<line>Their way back to the harem.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>					If the King </line>
<line>Prove victor, as it seems even now he must, </line>
<line>And miss his own Ionian, we are doomed </line>
<line>To worse than captive rebels.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>Let us trace them: </line>
<line>She cannot be fled far; and, found, she makes </line>
<line>A richer prize to our soft sovereign </line>
<line>Than his recovered kingdom.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Alt.</speaker>
<line>Baal himself </line>
<line>Ne'er fought more fiercely to win empire, than </line>
<line>His silken son to save it: he defies </line>
<line>All augury of foes or friends; and like </line>
<line>The close and sultry summer's day, which bodes </line>
<line>A twilight tempest, bursts forth in such thunder </line>
<line>As sweeps the air and deluges the earth. </line>
<line>The man's inscrutable.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sfe.</speaker>
<line>					Not more than others. </line>
<line>All are the sons of circumstance: away--- </line>
<line>Let's seek the slave out, or prepare to be </line>
<line>Tortured for his infatuation, and </line>
<line>Condemned without a crime. </line></sp>
    <stage>Exeunt.</stage><stage>Enter <strong>Salemenes</strong> and Soldiers, etc.</stage>
    <sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					The triumph is </line>
<line>Flattering: they are beaten backward from the palace, </line>
<line>And we have opened regular access </line>
<line>To the troops stationed on the other side </line>
<line>Euphrates, who may still be true; nay, must be, </line>
<line>When they hear of our victory. But where </line>
<line>Is the chief victor? where's the King?</line></sp>
        <stage>Enter <strong>Sardanapalus</strong>, cum suis, etc., and <strong>Myrrha</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Here, brother.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Unhurt, I hope.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Not quite; but let it pass. </line>
<line>We've cleared the palace---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And I trust the city. </line>
<line>Our numbers gather; and I've ordered onward </line>
<line>A cloud of Parthians, hitherto reserved, </line>
<line>All fresh and fiery, to be poured upon them </line>
<line>In their retreat, which soon will be a flight.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>It is already, or at least they marched </line>
<line>Faster than I could follow with my Bactrians, </line>
<line>Who spared no speed. I am spent: give me a seat.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>There stands the throne, Sire.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis no place to rest on, </line>
<line>For mind nor body: let me have a couch, </line>
<stage>They place a seat.</stage>
<line>A peasant's stool, I care not what: so---now</line>
<line>I breathe more freely.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>This great hour has proved </line>
<line>The brightest and most glorious of your life.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And the most tiresome. Where's my cupbearer? </line>
<line>Bring me some water.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<stage>smiling</stage>.
<line>					'Tis the first time he</line>
<line>Ever had such an order: even I, </line>
<line>Your most austere of counsellors, would now </line>
<line>Suggest a purpler beverage.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Blood---doubtless. </line>
<line>But there's enough of that shed; as for wine, </line>
<line>I have learned to-night the price of the pure element: </line>
<line>Thrice have I drank of it, and thrice renewed, </line>
<line>With greater strength than the grape ever gave me, </line>
<line>My charge upon the rebels. Where's the soldier </line>
<line>Who gave me water in his helmet?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>One of the Guards.</speaker>
<line>Slain, Sire! </line>
<line>An arrow pierced his brain, while, scattering </line>
<line>The last drops from his helm, he stood in act </line>
<line>To place it on his brows.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Slain! unrewarded! </line>
<line>And slain to serve my thirst: that's hard, poor slave! </line>
<line>Had he but lived, I would have gorged him with </line>
<line>Gold: all the gold of earth could ne'er repay </line>
<line>The pleasure of that draught; for I was parched </line>
<line>As I am now. </line>
<stage>They bring water---he drinks.</stage>
<line>I live again---from henceforth</line> 
<line>The goblet I reserve for hours of love, </line>
<line>But war on water.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And that bandage, Sire, </line>
<line>Which girds your arm?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>A scratch from brave Beleses.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Oh! he is wounded!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Not too much of that; </line>
<line>And yet it feels a little stiff and painful, </line>
<line>Now I am cooler.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>You have bound it with---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>The fillet of my diadem: the first time </line>
<line>That ornament was ever aught to me, </line>
<line>Save an incumbrance.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<stage>to the Attendants.</stage>
<line>					Summon speedily</line> 
<line>A leech of the most skilful: pray, retire: </line>
<line>I will unbind your wound and tend it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Do so, </line>
<line>For now it throbs sufficiently: but what </line>
<line>Know'st thou of wounds? yet wherefore do I ask? </line>
<line>Know'st thou, my brother, where I lighted on </line>
<line>This minion?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Herding with the other females, </line>
<line>Like frightened antelopes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No: like the dam </line>
<line>Of the young lion, femininely raging </line>
<line>(And femininely meaneth furiously, </line>
<line>Because all passions in excess are female,) </line>
<line>Against the hunter flying with her cub, </line>
<line>She urged on with her voice and gesture, and </line>
<line>Her floating hair and flashing eyes, the soldiers, </line>
<line>In the pursuit.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Indeed!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>You see, this night </line>
<line>Made warriors of more than me. I paused </line>
<line>To look upon her, and her kindled cheek; </line>
<line>Her large black eyes, that flashed through her long hair </line>
<line>As it streamed o'er her; her blue veins that rose </line>
<line>Along her most transparent brow; her nostril </line>
<line>Dilated from its symmetry; her lips </line>
<line>Apart; her voice that clove through all the din, </line>
<line>As a lute pierceth through the cymbal's clash, </line>
<line>Jarred but not drowned by the loud brattling; her </line>
<line>Waved arms, more dazzling with their own born whiteness </line>
<line>Than the steel her hand held, which she caught up </line>
<line>From a dead soldier's grasp;---all these things made </line>
<line>Her seem unto the troops a prophetess </line>
<line>Of victory, or Victory herself, </line>
<line>Come down to hail us hers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>aside</stage>
<line>This is too much. </line>
<line>Again the love-fit's on him, and all's lost, </line>
<line>Unless we turn his thoughts.</line>
<stage>Aloud.</stage>
<line>But pray thee, Sire,</line>
<line>Think of your wound---you said even now 'twas painful.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That's true, too; but I must not think of it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I have looked to all things needful, and will now </line>
<line>Receive reports of progress made in such </line>
<line>Orders as I had given, and then return </line>
<line>To hear your further pleasure.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Be it so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>in retiring</stage>
<line>Myrrha!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Prince!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>You have shown a soul to-night, </line>
<line>Which, were he not my sister's lord--- But now </line>
<line>I have no time: thou lovest the King?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I love </line>
<line>Sardanapalus.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>But wouldst have him King still?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I would not have him less than what he should be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Well then, to have him King, and yours, and all </line>
<line>He should, or should not be; to have him <em>live,</em></line>
<line>Let him not sink back into luxury. </line>
<line>You have more power upon his spirit than </line>
<line>Wisdom within these walls, or fierce rebellion </line>
<line>Raging without: look well that he relapse not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>There needed not the voice of Salemenes </line>
<line>To urge me on to this: I will not fail. </line>
<line>All that a woman's weakness can---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Is power </line>
<line>Omnipotent o'er such a heart as his: </line>
<line>Exert it wisely. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Myrrha! what, at whispers </line>
<line>With my stern brother? I shall soon be jealous.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Myr.
</speaker><stage>smiling</stage>
<line>You have cause, Sire; for on the earth there breathes not </line>
<line>A man more worthy of a woman's love, </line>
<line>A soldier's trust, a subject's reverence, </line>
<line>A king's esteem---the whole world's admiration!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Praise him, but not so warmly. I must not </line>
<line>Hear those sweet lips grow eloquent in aught </line>
<line>That throws me into shade; yet you speak truth.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And now retire, to have your wound looked to, </line>
<line>Pray lean on me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes, love! but not from pain.</line></sp>
<stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
</div>
</div><div type="act"><head>ACT IV.</head>
<div type="scene"><head>Scene I.</head>
<stage><strong>Sardanapalus</strong> discovered sleeping upon a Couch, and occasionally disturbed in his slumbers, with <strong>Myrrha</strong> watching.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Myr.
</speaker><stage>sola, gazing</stage>
<line>I have stolen upon his rest, if rest it be, </line>
<line>Which thus convulses slumber: shall I wake him? </line>
<line>No, he seems calmer. Oh, thou God of Quiet! </line>
<line>Whose reign is o'er sealed eyelids and soft dreams, </line>
<line>Or deep, deep sleep, so as to be unfathomed, </line>
<line>Look like thy brother, Death,---so still, so stirless--- </line>
<line>For then we are happiest, as it may be, we </line>
<line>Are happiest of all within the realm </line>
<line>Of thy stern, silent, and unwakening Twin. </line>
<line>Again he moves---again the play of pain </line>
<line>Shoots o'er his features, as the sudden gust </line>
<line>Crisps the reluctant lake that lay so calm </line>
<line>Beneath the mountain shadow; or the blast </line>
<line>Ruffles the autumn leaves, that drooping cling </line>
<line>Faintly and motionless to their loved boughs. </line>
<line>I must awake him---yet not yet; who knows </line>
<line>From what I rouse him? It seems pain; but if </line>
<line>I quicken him to heavier pain? The fever </line>
<line>Of this tumultuous night, the grief too of </line>
<line>His wound, though slight, may cause all this, and shake </line>
<line>Me more to see than him to suffer. No: </line>
<line>Let Nature use her own maternal means, </line>
<line>And I await to second, not disturb her.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>awakening</stage>
<line>Not so---although he multiplied the stars,</line> 
<line>And gave them to me as a realm to share </line>
<line>From you and with you! I would not so purchase </line>
<line>The empire of Eternity. Hence---hence--- </line>
<line>Old Hunter of the earliest brutes! and ye, </line>
<line>Who hunted fellow-creatures as if brutes! </line>
<line>Once bloody mortals---and now bloodier idols, </line>
<line>If your priests lie not! And thou, ghastly Beldame! </line>
<line>Dripping with dusky gore, and trampling on </line>
<line>The carcasses of Inde---away! away! </line>
<line>Where am I? Where the spectres? Where---No---that </line>
<line>Is no false phantom: I should know it 'midst </line>
<line>All that the dead dare gloomily raise up </line>
<line>From their black gulf to daunt the living. Myrrha!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Alas! thou art pale, and on thy brow the drops </line>
<line>Gather like night dew. My beloved, hush--- </line>
<line>Calm thee. Thy speech seems of another world, </line>
<line>And thou art lord of this. Be of good cheer; </line>
<line>All will go well.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Thy <em>hand</em>---so---'tis thy hand;</line>
<line>'Tis flesh; grasp---clasp---yet closer, till I feel </line>
<line>Myself that which I was.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>At least know me </line>
<line>For what I am, and ever must be---thine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I know it now. I know this life again. </line>
<line>Ah, Myrrha! I have been where we shall be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>			My lord!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I've been i' the grave---where worms are lords </line>
<line>And kings are---But I did not deem it so; </line>
<line>I thought 'twas nothing.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>So it is; except </line>
<line>Unto the timid, who anticipate </line>
<line>That which may never be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Oh, Myrrha! if </line>
<line>Sleep shows such things, what may not Death disclose?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I know no evil Death can show, which Life </line>
<line>Has not already shown to those who live </line>
<line>Embodied longest. If there be indeed </line>
<line>A shore where Mind survives, 'twill be as Mind </line>
<line>All unincorporate: or if there flits </line>
<line>A shadow of this cumbrous clog of clay, </line>
<line>Which stalks, methinks, between our souls and heaven, </line>
<line>And fetters us to earth---at least the phantom, </line>
<line>Whate'er it have to fear, will not fear Death.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I fear it not; but I have felt---have seen--- </line>
<line>A legion of the dead.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And so have I. </line>
<line>The dust we tread upon was once alive, </line>
<line>And wretched. But proceed: what hast thou seen? </line>
<line>Speak it, 'twill lighten thy dimmed mind.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Methought---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>			Yet pause, thou art tired---in pain---exhausted; all </line>
<line>Which can impair both strength and spirit: seek </line>
<line>Rather to sleep again.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Not now---I would not </line>
<line>Dream; though I know it now to be a dream </line>
<line>What I have dreamt:---and canst thou bear to hear it?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I can bear all things, dreams of life or death, </line>
<line>Which I participate with you in semblance </line>
<line>Or full reality.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And this looked real, </line>
<line>I tell you: after that these eyes were open, </line>
<line>I saw them in their flight---for then they fled.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Say on.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I saw, that is, I dreamed myself </line>
<line>Here---here---even where we are, guests as we were, </line>
<line>Myself a host that deemed himself but guest, </line>
<line>Willing to equal all in social freedom; </line>
<line>But, on my right hand and my left, instead </line>
<line>Of thee and Zames, and our customed meeting, </line>
<line>Was ranged on my left hand a haughty, dark, </line>
<line>And deadly face; I could not recognise it, </line>
<line>Yet I had seen it, though I knew not where: </line>
<line>The features were a Giant's, and the eye </line>
<line>Was still, yet lighted; his long locks curled down </line>
<line>On his vast bust, whence a huge quiver rose </line>
<line>With shaft-heads feathered from the eagle's wing, </line>
<line>That peeped up bristling through his serpent hair. </line>
<line>I invited him to fill the cup which stood </line>
<line>Between us, but he answered not; I filled it; </line>
<line>He took it not, but stared upon me, till </line>
<line>I trembled at the fixed glare of his eye: </line>
<line>I frowned upon him as a king should frown; </line>
<line>He frowned not in his turn, but looked upon me </line>
<line>With the same aspect, which appalled me more, </line>
<line>Because it changed not; and I turned for refuge </line>
<line>To milder guests, and sought them on the right, </line>
<line>Where thou wert wont to be. But---</line></sp>
<stage>He pauses.</stage><sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					What instead?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>In thy own chair---thy own place in the banquet--- </line>
<line>I sought thy sweet face in the circle---but </line>
<line>Instead---a grey-haired, withered, bloody-eyed, </line>
<line>And bloody-handed, ghastly, ghostly thing, </line>
<line>Female in garb, and crowned upon the brow, </line>
<line>Furrowed with years, yet sneering with the passion </line>
<line>Of vengeance, leering too with that of lust, </line>
<line>Sate:---my veins curdled.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Is this all?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Upon </line>
<line>Her right hand---her lank, bird-like, right hand---stood </line>
<line>A goblet, bubbling o'er with blood; and on </line>
<line>Her left, another, filled with---what I saw not, </line>
<line>But turned from it and her. But all along </line>
<line>The table sate a range of crownéd wretches, </line>
<line>Of various aspects, but of one expression.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And felt you not this a mere vision?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					No: </line>
<line>It was so palpable, I could have touched them. </line>
<line>I turned from one face to another, in </line>
<line>The hope to find at last one which I knew </line>
<line>Ere I saw theirs: but no---all turned upon me, </line>
<line>And stared, but neither ate nor drank, but stared, </line>
<line>Till I grew stone, as they seemed half to be, </line>
<line>Yet breathing stone, for I felt life in them, </line>
<line>And life in me: there was a horrid kind </line>
<line>Of sympathy between us, as if they </line>
<line>Had lost a part of death to come to me, </line>
<line>And I the half of life to sit by them. </line>
<line>We were in an existence all apart </line>
<line>From heaven or earth---And rather let me see </line>
<line>Death all than such a being!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And the end?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>At last I sate, marble, as they, when rose </line>
<line>The Hunter and the Crone; and smiling on me--- </line>
<line>Yes, the enlarged but noble aspect of </line>
<line>The Hunter smiled upon me---I should say, </line>
<line>His lips, for his eyes moved not---and the woman's </line>
<line>Thin lips relaxed to something like a smile. </line>
<line>Both rose, and the crowned figures on each hand </line>
<line>Rose also, as if aping their chief shades--- </line>
<line>Mere mimics even in death---but I sate still: </line>
<line>A desperate courage crept through every limb, </line>
<line>And at the last I feared them not, but laughed </line>
<line>Full in their phantom faces. But then---then </line>
<line>The Hunter laid his hand on mine: I took it, </line>
<line>And grasped it---but it melted from my own; </line>
<line>While he too vanished, and left nothing but </line>
<line>The memory of a hero, for he looked so.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And was: the ancestor of heroes, too, </line>
<line>And thine no less.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Aye, Myrrha, but the woman, </line>
<line>The female who remained, she flew upon me, </line>
<line>And burnt my lips up with her noisome kisses; </line>
<line>And, flinging down the goblets on each hand, </line>
<line>Methought their poisons flowed around us, till </line>
<line>Each formed a hideous river. Still she clung; </line>
<line>The other phantoms, like a row of statues, </line>
<line>Stood dull as in our temples, but she still </line>
<line>Embraced me, while I shrunk from her, as if, </line>
<line>In lieu of her remote descendant, I </line>
<line>Had been the son who slew her for her incest. </line>
<line>Then---then---a chaos of all loathsome things </line>
<line>Thronged thick and shapeless: I was dead, yet feeling--- </line>
<line>Buried, and raised again---consumed by worms, </line>
<line>Purged by the flames, and withered in the air! </line>
<line>I can fix nothing further of my thoughts, </line>
<line>Save that I longed for thee, and sought for thee, </line>
<line>In all these agonies,---and woke and found thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>So shalt thou find me ever at thy side, </line>
<line>Here and hereafter, if the last may be. </line>
<line>But think not of these things---the mere creations </line>
<line>Of late events, acting upon a frame </line>
<line>Unused by toil, yet over-wrought by toil--- </line>
<line>Such as might try the sternest.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I am better.</line> 
<line>Now that I see thee once more, <em>what was seen</em></line>
<line>Seems nothing.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Is the king so soon awake?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes, brother, and I would I had not slept; </line>
<line>For all the predecessors of our line </line>
<line>Rose up, methought, to drag me down to them. </line>
<line>My father was amongst them, too; but he, </line>
<line>I know not why, kept from me, leaving me </line>
<line>Between the hunter-founder of our race, </line>
<line>And her, the homicide and husband-killer, </line>
<line>Whom you call glorious.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					So I term you also, </line>
<line>Now you have shown a spirit like to hers. </line>
<line>By day-break I propose that we set forth, </line>
<line>And charge once more the rebel crew, who still </line>
<line>Keep gathering head, repulsed, but not quite quelled.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>How wears the night?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					There yet remain some hours </line>
<line>Of darkness: use them for your further rest.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No, not to-night, if 'tis not gone: methought </line>
<line>I passed hours in that vision.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Scarcely one; </line>
<line>I watched by you: it was a heavy hour, </line>
<line>But an hour only.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Let us then hold council; </line>
<line>To-morrow we set forth.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>But ere that time, </line>
<line>I had a grace to seek.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Tis granted.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Hear it </line>
<line>Ere you reply too readily; and 'tis</line>
<line>For <em>your</em> ear only.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Prince, I take my leave.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Myrrha</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>That slave deserves her freedom.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Freedom only! </line>
<line>That slave deserves to share a throne.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Your patience--- </line>
<line>'Tis not yet vacant, and 'tis of its partner </line>
<line>I come to speak with you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					How! of the Queen?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Even so. I judged it fitting for their safety, </line>
<line>That, ere the dawn, she sets forth with her children </line>
<line>For Paphlagonia, where our kinsman Cotta </line>
<line>Governs; and there, at all events, secure </line>
<line>My nephews and your sons their lives, and with them </line>
<line>Their just pretensions to the crown in case---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I perish---as is probable: well thought--- </line>
<line>Let them set forth with a sure escort.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>That </line>
<line>Is all provided, and the galley ready </line>
<line>To drop down the Euphrates; but ere they </line>
<line>Depart, will you not see---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My sons? It may </line>
<line>Unman my heart, and the poor boys will weep; </line>
<line>And what can I reply to comfort them, </line>
<line>Save with some hollow hopes, and ill-worn smiles? </line>
<line>You know I cannot feign.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>But you can feel! </line>
<line>At least, I trust so: in a word, the Queen </line>
<line>Requests to see you ere you part---for ever.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Unto what end? what purpose? I will grant </line>
<line>Aught---all that she can ask---but such a meeting.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>You know, or ought to know, enough of women, </line>
<line>Since you have studied them so steadily, </line>
<line>That what they ask in aught that touches on </line>
<line>The heart, is dearer to their feelings or </line>
<line>Their fancy, than the whole external world. </line>
<line>I think as you do of my sister's wish; </line>
<line>But 'twas her wish---she is my sister---you </line>
<line>Her husband---will you grant it?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Twill be useless: </line>
<line>But let her come.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I go. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					We have lived asunder</line>
<line>Too long to meet again---and <em>now</em> to meet!</line>
<line>Have I not cares enow, and pangs enow, </line>
<line>To bear alone, that we must mingle sorrows, </line>
<line>Who have ceased to mingle love?</line></sp>
<stage>Re-enter <strong>Salemenes</strong> and <strong>Zarina</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					My sister! Courage: </line>
<line>Shame not our blood with trembling, but remember </line>
<line>From whence we sprung. The Queen is present, Sire.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>I pray thee, brother, leave me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Since you ask it.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Salemenes</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Alone with him! How many a year has passed, </line>
<line>Though we are still so young, since we have met, </line>
<line>Which I have worn in widowhood of heart. </line>
<line>He loved me not: yet he seems little changed--- </line>
<line>Changed to me only---would the change were mutual! </line>
<line>He speaks not---scarce regards me---not a word, </line>
<line>Nor look---yet he <em>was</em> soft of voice and aspect,</line>
<line>Indifferent, not austere. My Lord!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Zarina!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>No,</line>
<em>not</em>
Zarina---do not say Zarina.
<line>That tone---That word---annihilate long years, </line>
<line>And things which make them longer.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis too late </line>
<line>To think of these past dreams. Let's not reproach--- </line>
<line>That is, reproach me not---for the <em>last</em> time---</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>And <em>first</em>. I ne'er reproached you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis most true; </line>
<line>And that reproof comes heavier on my heart </line>
<line>Than---But our hearts are not in our own power.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Nor hands; but I gave both.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Your brother said </line>
<line>It was your will to see me, ere you went </line>
<line>From Nineveh with---</line></sp>
<stage>He hesitates.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					Our children: it is true. </line>
<line>I wish to thank you that you have not divided </line>
<line>My heart from all that's left it now to love--- </line>
<line>Those who are yours and mine, who look like you, </line>
<line>And look upon me as you looked upon me </line>
<line>Once---but <em>they</em> have not changed.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Nor ever will. </line>
<line>I fain would have them dutiful.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>I cherish </line>
<line>Those infants, not alone from the blind love </line>
<line>Of a fond mother, but as a fond woman. </line>
<line>They are now the only tie between us.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Deem not </line>
<line>I have not done you justice: rather make them </line>
<line>Resemble your own line than their own Sire. </line>
<line>I trust them with you---to you: fit them for </line>
<line>A throne, or, if that be denied---You have heard </line>
<line>Of this night's tumults?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>I had half forgotten, </line>
<line>And could have welcomed any grief save yours, </line>
<line>Which gave me to behold your face again.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>The throne---I say it not in fear---but 'tis </line>
<line>In peril: they perhaps may never mount it; </line>
<line>But let them not for this lose sight of it. </line>
<line>I will dare all things to bequeath it them; </line>
<line>But if I fail, then they must win it back </line>
<line>Bravely---and, won, wear it wisely, not as I </line>
<line>Have wasted down my royalty.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					They ne'er </line>
<line>Shall know from me of aught but what may honour </line>
<line>Their father's memory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Rather let them hear </line>
<line>The truth from you than from a trampling world. </line>
<line>If they be in adversity, they'll learn </line>
<line>Too soon the scorn of crowds for crownless Princes, </line>
<line>And find that all their father's sins are theirs. </line>
<line>My boys!---I could have borne it were I childless.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Oh! do not say so---do not poison all </line>
<line>My peace left, by unwishing that thou wert </line>
<line>A father. If thou conquerest, they shall reign, </line>
<line>And honour him who saved the realm for them, </line>
<line>So little cared for as his own; and if---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Tis lost, all Earth will cry out, "thank your father!" </line>
<line>And they will swell the echo with a curse.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>That they shall never do; but rather honour </line>
<line>The name of him, who, dying like a king, </line>
<line>In his last hours did more for his own memory </line>
<line>Than many monarchs in a length of days, </line>
<line>Which date the flight of time, but make no annals.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Our annals draw perchance unto their close; </line>
<line>But at the least, whate'er the past, their end </line>
<line>Shall be like their beginning---memorable.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Yet, be not rash---be careful of your life, </line>
<line>Live but for those who love.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And who are they? </line>
<line>A slave, who loves from passion---I'll not say </line>
<line>Ambition---she has seen thrones shake, and loves; </line>
<line>A few friends who have revelled till we are </line>
<line>As one, for they are nothing if I fall; </line>
<line>A brother I have injured---children whom </line>
<line>I have neglected, and a spouse---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Who loves.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And pardons?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					I have never thought of this, </line>
<line>And cannot pardon till I have condemned.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My wife!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					Now blessings on thee for that word! </line>
<line>I never thought to hear it more---from thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Oh! thou wilt hear it from my subjects. Yes--- </line>
<line>These slaves whom I have nurtured, pampered, fed, </line>
<line>And swoln with peace, and gorged with plenty, till </line>
<line>They reign themselves---all monarchs in their mansions--- </line>
<line>Now swarm forth in rebellion, and demand </line>
<line>His death, who made their lives a jubilee; </line>
<line>While the few upon whom I have no claim </line>
<line>Are faithful! This is true, yet monstrous.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis </line>
<line>Perhaps too natural; for benefits </line>
<line>Turn poison in bad minds.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And good ones make </line>
<line>Good out of evil. Happier than the bee, </line>
<line>Which hives not but from wholesome flowers.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Then reap </line>
<line>The honey, nor inquire whence 'tis derived. </line>
<line>Be satisfied---you are not all abandoned.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My life insures me that. How long, bethink you, </line>
<line>Were not I yet a king, should I be mortal; </line>
<line>That is, where mortals <em>are</em>, not where they must be?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>I know not. But yet live for my---that is, </line>
<line>Your children's sake!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>My gentle, wronged Zarina! </line>
<line>I am the very slave of Circumstance </line>
<line>And Impulse---borne away with every breath! </line>
<line>Misplaced upon the throne---misplaced in life. </line>
<line>I know not what I could have been, but feel </line>
<line>I am not what I should be---let it end. </line>
<line>But take this with thee: if I was not formed </line>
<line>To prize a love like thine, a mind like thine, </line>
<line>Nor dote even on thy beauty---as I've doted </line>
<line>On lesser charms, for no cause save that such </line>
<line>Devotion was a duty, and I hated </line>
<line>All that looked like a chain for me or others </line>
<line>(This even Rebellion must avouch); yet hear </line>
<line>These words, perhaps among my last---that none </line>
<line>E'er valued more thy virtues, though he knew not </line>
<line>To profit by them---as the miner lights </line>
<line>Upon a vein of virgin ore, discovering </line>
<line>That which avails him nothing: he hath found it, </line>
<line>But 'tis not his---but some superior's, who </line>
<line>Placed him to dig, but not divide the wealth </line>
<line>Which sparkles at his feet; nor dare he lift </line>
<line>Nor poise it, but must grovel on, upturning </line>
<line>The sullen earth.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Oh! if thou hast at length </line>
<line>Discovered that my love is worth esteem, </line>
<line>I ask no more---but let us hence together,</line> 
<line>And <em>I</em>---let me say <em>we</em>---shall yet be happy.</line>
<line>Assyria is not all the earth---we'll find </line>
<line>A world out of our own---and be more blessed </line>
<line>Than I have ever been, or thou, with all </line>
<line>An empire to indulge thee.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Salemenes</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					I must part ye--- </line>
<line>The moments, which must not be lost, are passing.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Inhuman brother! wilt thou thus weigh out </line>
<line>Instants so high and blest?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Blest!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>He hath been </line>
<line>So gentle with me, that I cannot think </line>
<line>Of quitting.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>So---this feminine farewell </line>
<line>Ends as such partings end, in</line>
<em>no</em>
departure.
<line>I thought as much, and yielded against all </line>
<line>My better bodings. But it must not be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Not be?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Remain, and perish---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>With my husband---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And children.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					Alas!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Hear me, sister, like </line>
<line><em>My</em> sister:---all's prepared to make your safety</line>
<line>Certain, and of the boys too, our last hopes; </line>
<line>'Tis not a single question of mere feeling, </line>
<line>Though that were much---but 'tis a point of state: </line>
<line>The rebels would do more to seize upon </line>
<line>The offspring of their sovereign, and so crush---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Ah! do not name it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Well, then, mark me: when </line>
<line>They are safe beyond the Median's grasp, the rebels </line>
<line>Have missed their chief aim---the extinction of </line>
<line>The line of Nimrod. Though the present King </line>
<line>Fall, his sons live---for victory and vengeance.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>But could not I remain, alone?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					What! leave </line>
<line>Your children, with two parents and yet orphans--- </line>
<line>In a strange land---so young, so distant?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					No--- </line>
<line>My heart will break.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Now you know all---decide.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Zarina, he hath spoken well, and we </line>
<line>Must yield awhile to this necessity. </line>
<line>Remaining here, you may lose all; departing, </line>
<line>You save the better part of what is left, </line>
<line>To both of us, and to such loyal hearts </line>
<line>As yet beat in these kingdoms.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					The time presses.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Go, then. If e'er we meet again, perhaps </line>
<line>I may be worthier of you---and, if not, </line>
<line>Remember that my faults, though not atoned for,</line> 
<line>Are <em>ended</em>. Yet, I dread thy nature will</line>
<line>Grieve more above the blighted name and ashes </line>
<line>Which once were mightiest in Assyria---than--- </line>
<line>But I grow womanish again, and must not; </line>
<line>I must learn sternness now. My sins have all</line> 
<line>Been of the softer order---<em>hide</em> thy tears---</line>
<line>I do not bid thee <em>not</em> to shed them---'twere</line>
<line>Easier to stop Euphrates at its source </line>
<line>Than one tear of a true and tender heart--- </line>
<line>But let me not behold them; they unman me </line>
<line>Here when I had remanned myself. My brother, </line>
<line>Lead her away.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>					Oh, God! I never shall </line>
<line>Behold him more!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>striving to conduct her</stage>
<line>Nay, sister, I <em>must</em> be obeyed.</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>I must remain---away! you shall not hold me. </line>
<line>What, shall he die alone?---<em>I</em> live alone?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>He shall <em>not die alone</em>; but lonely you</line>
<line>Have lived for years.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>That's false! I knew <em>he</em> lived,</line>
<line>And lived upon his image---let me go!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sal.
</speaker><stage>conducting her off the stage</stage>
<line>Nay, then, then, I must use some fraternal force, </line>
<line>Which you will pardon.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>Never. Help me! Oh! </line>
<line>Sardanapalus, wilt thou thus behold me </line>
<line>Torn from thee?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Nay---then all is lost again, </line>
<line>If that this moment is not gained.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Zar.</speaker>
<line>My brain turns--- </line>
    <line>My eyes fail---where is he? </line></sp>
<stage>She faints.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>advancing</stage>
<line>					No---set her down; </line>
<line>She's dead---and you have slain her.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis the mere </line>
<line>Faintness of o'erwrought passion: in the air </line>
<line>She will recover. Pray, keep back.---<stage>Aside.</stage> I must</line> 
<line>Avail myself of this sole moment to </line>
<line>Bear her to where her children are embarked, </line>
    <line>I' the royal galley on the river.</line></sp>
<stage><strong>Salemenes</strong> bears her off.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker><stage>solus</stage><line>					This, too---</line>
<line>And this too must I suffer---I, who never </line>
<line>Inflicted purposely on human hearts </line>
<line>A voluntary pang! But that is false--- </line>
<line>She loved me, and I loved her.---Fatal passion!</line> 
<line>Why dost thou not expire at <em>once</em> in hearts</line>
<line>Which thou hast lighted up at once? Zarina! </line>
<line>I must pay dearly for the desolation </line>
<line>Now brought upon thee. Had I never loved </line>
<line>But thee, I should have been an unopposed </line>
<line>Monarch of honouring nations. To what gulfs </line>
<line>A single deviation from the track </line>
<line>Of human duties leads even those who claim </line>
<line>The homage of mankind as their born due, </line>
<line>And find it, till they forfeit it themselves!</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Myrrha</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker><line><em>You</em> here! Who called you?</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>No one---but I heard </line>
<line>Far off a voice of wail and lamentation, </line>
<line>And thought---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>It forms no portion of your duties </line>
<line>To enter here till sought for.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Though I might, </line>
<line>Perhaps, recall some softer words of yours</line> 
<line>(Although they <em>too were chiding</em>), which reproved me,</line>
<line>			Because I ever dreaded to intrude; </line>
<line>Resisting my own wish and your injunction </line>
<line>To heed no time nor presence, but approach you </line>
<line>Uncalled for:---I retire.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yet stay---being here. </line>
<line>I pray you pardon me: events have soured me </line>
<line>Till I wax peevish---heed it not: I shall </line>
<line>Soon be myself again.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I wait with patience, </line>
<line>What I shall see with pleasure.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Scarce a moment </line>
<line>Before your entrance in this hall, Zarina, </line>
<line>Queen of Assyria, departed hence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Ah!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Wherefore do you start?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Did I do so?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Twas well you entered by another portal, </line>
<line>Else you had met. That pang at least is spared her!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I know to feel for her.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That is too much, </line>
<line>And beyond nature---'tis nor mutual </line>
<line>Nor possible. You cannot pity her, </line>
<line>Nor she aught but---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Despise the favourite slave? </line>
<line>Not more than I have ever scorned myself.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>			Scorned! what, to be the envy of your sex, </line>
<line>And lord it o'er the heart of the World's lord?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Were you the lord of twice ten thousand worlds--- </line>
<line>As you are like to lose the one you swayed--- </line>
<line>I did abase myself as much in being </line>
<line>Your paramour, as though you were a peasant--- </line>
<line>Nay, more, if that the peasant were a Greek.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>You talk it well---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					And truly.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>In the hour </line>
<line>Of man's adversity all things grow daring </line>
<line>Against the falling; but as I am not </line>
<line>Quite fall'n, nor now disposed to bear reproaches, </line>
<line>Perhaps because I merit them too often, </line>
<line>Let us then part while peace is still between us.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Part!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Have not all past human beings parted, </line>
<line>And must not all the present one day part?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Why?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					For your safety, which I will have looked to, </line>
<line>With a strong escort to your native land; </line>
<line>And such gifts, as, if you had not been all </line>
<line>A Queen, shall make your dowry worth a kingdom.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I pray you talk not thus.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					The Queen is gone: </line>
<line>You need not shame to follow. I would fall </line>
<line>Alone---I seek no partners but in pleasure.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And I no pleasure but in parting not. </line>
<line>You shall not force me from you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Think well of it--- </line>
<line>It soon may be too late.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>So let it be; </line>
<line>For then you cannot separate me from you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And will not; but I thought you wished it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					I!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>You spoke of your abasement.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					And I feel it </line>
<line>Deeply---more deeply than all things but love.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then fly from it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					'Twill not recall the past--- </line>
<line>'Twill not restore my honour, nor my heart. </line>
<line>No---here I stand or fall. If that you conquer, </line>
<line>I live to joy in your great triumph: should </line>
<line>Your lot be different, I'll not weep, but share it. </line>
<line>You did not doubt me a few hours ago.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Your courage never---nor your love till now; </line>
<line>And none could make me doubt it save yourself. </line>
<line>Those words---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Were words. I pray you, let the proofs </line>
<line>Be in the past acts you were pleased to praise </line>
<line>This very night, and in my further bearing, </line>
<line>Beside, wherever you are borne by fate.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I am content: and, trusting in my cause, </line>
<line>Think we may yet be victors and return </line>
<line>To peace---the only victory I covet. </line>
<line>To me war is no glory---conquest no </line>
<line>Renown. To be forced thus to uphold my right </line>
<line>Sits heavier on my heart than all the wrongs </line>
<line>These men would bow me down with. Never, never </line>
<line>Can I forget this night, even should I live </line>
<line>To add it to the memory of others. </line>
<line>I thought to have made mine inoffensive rule </line>
<line>An era of sweet peace 'midst bloody annals, </line>
<line>A green spot amidst desert centuries, </line>
<line>On which the Future would turn back and smile, </line>
<line>And cultivate, or sigh when it could not </line>
<line>Recall Sardanapalus' golden reign. </line>
<line>I thought to have made my realm a paradise, </line>
<line>And every moon an epoch of new pleasures. </line>
<line>I took the rabble's shouts for love---the breath </line>
<line>Of friends for truth---the lips of woman for </line>
<line>My only guerdon---so they are, my Myrrha: </line>
<stage>He kisses her.</stage>
<line>Kiss me. Now let them take my realm and life!</line> 
<line>They shall have both, but never <em>thee!</em></line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>No, never! </line>
<line>Man may despoil his brother man of all </line>
<line>That 's great or glittering---kingdoms fall, hosts yield, </line>
<line>Friends fail---slaves fly---and all betray---and, more </line>
<line>Than all, the most indebted---but a heart </line>
<line>That loves without self-love! 'Tis here---now prove it.</line></sp>
<stage>Enter <strong>Salemenes</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I sought you---How! <em>she</em> here again?</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Return not</line>
<line><em>Now</em> to reproof: methinks your aspect speaks</line>
<line>Of higher matter than a woman's presence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>The only woman whom it much imports me </line>
<line>At such a moment now is safe in absence--- </line>
<line>The Queen 's embarked.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And well? say that much.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Yes. </line>
<line>Her transient weakness has passed o'er; at least, </line>
<line>It settled into tearless silence: her </line>
<line>Pale face and glittering eye, after a glance </line>
<line>Upon her sleeping children, were still fixed </line>
<line>Upon the palace towers as the swift galley </line>
<line>Stole down the hurrying stream beneath the starlight; </line>
<line>But she said nothing.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Would I felt no more </line>
<line>Than she has said!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>'Tis now too late to feel. </line>
<line>Your feelings cannot cancel a sole pang: </line>
<line>To change them, my advices bring sure tidings </line>
<line>That the rebellious Medes and Chaldees, marshalled </line>
<line>By their two leaders, are already up </line>
<line>In arms again; and, serrying their ranks, </line>
<line>Prepare to attack: they have apparently </line>
<line>Been joined by other Satraps.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What! more rebels? </line>
<line>Let us be first, then.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>That were hardly prudent </line>
<line>Now, though it was our first intention. If </line>
<line>By noon to-morrow we are joined by those </line>
<line>I've sent for by sure messengers, we shall be </line>
<line>In strength enough to venture an attack, </line>
<line>Aye, and pursuit too; but, till then, my voice </line>
<line>Is to await the onset.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I detest </line>
<line>That waiting; though it seems so safe to fight </line>
<line>Behind high walls, and hurl down foes into </line>
<line>Deep fosses, or behold them sprawl on spikes </line>
<line>Strewed to receive them, still I like it not--- </line>
<line>My soul seems lukewarm; but when I set on them, </line>
<line>Though they were piled on mountains, I would have </line>
<line>A pluck at them, or perish in hot blood!--- </line>
<line>Let me then charge.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>You talk like a young soldier.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>			I am no soldier, but a man: speak not </line>
<line>Of soldiership, I loathe the word, and those </line>
<line>Who pride themselves upon it; but direct me </line>
<line>Where I may pour upon them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					You must spare </line>
<line>To expose your life too hastily; 'tis not </line>
<line>Like mine or any other subject's breath: </line>
<line>The whole war turns upon it---with it; this </line>
<line>Alone creates it, kindles, and may quench it--- </line>
<line>Prolong it---end it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then let us end both! </line>
<line>'Twere better thus, perhaps, than prolong either; </line>
<line>I'm sick of one, perchance of both.</line></sp>
<stage>A trumpet sounds without.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					Hark!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Let us </line>
<line>Reply, not listen.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And your wound!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Tis bound--- </line>
<line>'Tis healed---I had forgotten it. Away! </line>
<line>A leech's lancet would have scratched me deeper; </line>
<line>The slave that gave it might be well ashamed </line>
<line>To have struck so weakly.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Now, may none this hour </line>
<line>Strike with a better aim!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Aye, if we conquer; </line>
<line>But if not, they will only leave to me </line>
<line>A task they might have spared their king. Upon them!</line></sp>
<stage>Trumpet sounds again.</stage><sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I am with you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Ho, my arms! again, my arms!</line></sp>
<stage>Exeunt.</stage></div>
</div><div type="act"><head>ACT V.</head>
<div type="scene"><head>Scene I.</head>
<stage>---The same Hall in the Palace.</stage>
<stage><strong>Myrrha</strong> and <strong>Balea</strong></stage>
<sp><speaker>
Myr.
</speaker><stage>at a window</stage><line>The day at last has broken. What a night </line>
<line>Hath ushered it! How beautiful in heaven! </line>
<line>Though varied with a transitory storm, </line>
<line>More beautiful in that variety! </line>
<line>How hideous upon earth! where Peace and Hope, </line>
<line>And Love and Revel, in an hour were trampled </line>
<line>By human passions to a human chaos, </line>
<line>Not yet resolved to separate elements--- </line>
<line>'Tis warring still! And can the sun so rise, </line>
<line>So bright, so rolling back the clouds into </line>
<line>Vapours more lovely than the unclouded sky, </line>
<line>With golden pinnacles, and snowy mountains, </line>
<line>And billows purpler than the Ocean's, making </line>
<line>In heaven a glorious mockery of the earth, </line>
<line>So like we almost deem it permanent; </line>
<line>So fleeting, we can scarcely call it aught </line>
<line>Beyond a vision, 'tis so transiently </line>
<line>Scattered along the eternal vault: and yet </line>
<line>It dwells upon the soul, and soothes the soul, </line>
<line>And blends itself into the soul, until </line>
<line>Sunrise and sunset form the haunted epoch </line>
<line>Of Sorrow and of Love; which they who mark not, </line>
<line>Know not the realms where those twin genii </line>
<line>(Who chasten and who purify our hearts, </line>
<line>So that we would not change their sweet rebukes </line>
<line>For all the boisterous joys that ever shook </line>
<line>The air with clamour) build the palaces </line>
<line>Where their fond votaries repose and breathe </line>
<line>Briefly;---but in that brief cool calm inhale </line>
<line>Enough of heaven to enable them to bear </line>
<line>The rest of common, heavy, human hours, </line>
<line>And dream them through in placid sufferance, </line>
<line>Though seemingly employed like all the rest </line>
<line>Of toiling breathers in allotted tasks </line>
<line>Of pain or pleasure, <em>two</em> names for <em>one</em> feeling,</line>
<line>Which our internal, restless agony </line>
<line>Would vary in the sound, although the sense </line>
<line>Escapes our highest efforts to be happy.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>You muse right calmly: and can you so watch </line>
<line>The sunrise which may be our last?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					It is </line>
<line>Therefore that I so watch it, and reproach </line>
<line>Those eyes, which never may behold it more, </line>
<line>For having looked upon it oft, too oft, </line>
<line>Without the reverence and the rapture due </line>
<line>To that which keeps all earth from being as fragile </line>
<line>As I am in this form. Come, look upon it, </line>
<line>The Chaldee's God, which, when I gaze upon, </line>
<line>I grow almost a convert to your Baal.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>			As now he reigns in heaven, so once on earth </line>
<line>He swayed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					He sways it now for more, then; never </line>
<line>Had earthly monarch half the power and glory </line>
<line>Which centres in a single ray of his.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>Surely he is a God!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					So we Greeks deem too; </line>
<line>And yet I sometimes think that gorgeous orb </line>
<line>Must rather be the abode of Gods than one </line>
<line>Of the immortal sovereigns. Now he breaks </line>
<line>Through all the clouds, and fills my eyes with light </line>
<line>That shuts the world out. I can look no more.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>Hark! heard you not a sound?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					No, 'twas mere fancy; </line>
<line>They battle it beyond the wall, and not </line>
<line>As in late midnight conflict in the very </line>
<line>Chambers: the palace has become a fortress </line>
<line>Since that insidious hour; and here, within </line>
<line>The very centre, girded by vast courts </line>
<line>And regal halls of pyramid proportions, </line>
<line>Which must be carried one by one before </line>
<line>They penetrate to where they then arrived, </line>
<line>We are as much shut in even from the sound </line>
<line>Of peril as from glory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>But they reached </line>
<line>Thus far before.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Yes, by surprise, and were </line>
<line>Beat back by valour: now at once we have </line>
<line>Courage and vigilance to guard us.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>May they </line>
<line>Prosper!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>That is the prayer of many, and </line>
<line>The dread of more: it is an anxious hour; </line>
<line>I strive to keep it from my thoughts. Alas! </line>
<line>How vainly!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>It is said the King's demeanour </line>
<line>In the late action scarcely more appalled </line>
<line>The rebels than astonished his true subjects.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>'Tis easy to astonish or appal </line>
<line>The vulgar mass which moulds a horde of slaves; </line>
<line>But he did bravely.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>					Slew he not Beleses? </line>
<line>I heard the soldiers say he struck him down.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>The wretch was overthrown, but rescued to </line>
<line>Triumph, perhaps, o'er one who vanquished him </line>
<line>In fight, as he had spared him in his peril; </line>
<line>And by that heedless pity risked a crown.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>					Hark!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>You are right; some steps approach, but slowly.</line></sp>
    <stage>Enter Soldiers, bearing in <strong>Salemenes</strong> wounded, with a broken javelin in his side: they seat him upon one of the couches which furnish the Apartment.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Oh, Jove!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Bal.</speaker>
<line>					Then all is over.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>					That is false. </line>
<line>Hew down the slave who says so, if a soldier.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Spare him---he's none: a mere court butterfly, </line>
<line>That flutter in the pageant of a monarch.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Let him live on, then.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>So wilt thou, I trust.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I fain would live this hour out, and the event, </line>
<line>But doubt it. Wherefore did ye bear me here?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sol.</speaker>
<line>By the King's order. When the javelin struck you, </line>
<line>You fell and fainted: 'twas his strict command </line>
<line>To bear you to this hall.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>'Twas not ill done: </line>
<line>For seeming slain in that cold dizzy trance, </line>
<line>The sight might shake our soldiers---but---'tis vain, </line>
<line>I feel it ebbing!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Let me see the wound; </line>
<line>I am not quite skilless: in my native land </line>
<line>'Tis part of our instruction. War being constant, </line>
<line>We are nerved to look on such things.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sol.</speaker>
<line>Best extract </line>
<line>The javelin.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Hold! no, no, it cannot be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I am sped, then!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					With the blood that fast must follow </line>
<line>The extracted weapon, I do fear thy life.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And I</line>
<em>not</em>
. death. Where was the King when you
<line>Conveyed me from the spot where I was stricken?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sol.</speaker>
<line>Upon the same ground, and encouraging </line>
<line>With voice and gesture the dispirited troops </line>
<line>Who had seen you fall, and faltered back.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Whom heard ye </line>
<line>Named next to the command?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sol.</speaker>
<line>I did not hear.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Fly, then, and tell him, 'twas my last request </line>
<line>That Zames take my post until the junction, </line>
<line>So hoped for, yet delayed, of Ofratanes, </line>
<line>Satrap of Susa. Leave me here: our troops </line>
<line>Are not so numerous as to spare your absence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sol.</speaker>
<line>But Prince---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Hence, I say! Here 's a courtier and </line>
<line>A woman, the best chamber company. </line>
<line>As you would not permit me to expire </line>
<line>Upon the field, I'll have no idle soldiers </line>
<line>About my sick couch. Hence! and do my bidding!</line></sp>
<stage>Exeunt the Soldiers.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Gallant and glorious Spirit! must the earth </line>
<line>So soon resign thee?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Gentle Myrrha, 'tis </line>
<line>The end I would have chosen, had I saved </line>
<line>The monarch or the monarchy by this; </line>
<line>As 'tis, I have not outlived them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>You wax paler.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>Your hand; this broken weapon but prolongs </line>
<line>My pangs, without sustaining life enough </line>
<line>To make me useful: I would draw it forth </line>
<line>And my life with it, could I but hear how </line>
<line>The fight goes.</line></sp>
    <stage>Enter Sardanapalus and Soldiers.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					My best brother!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>And the battle </line>
<line>Is lost?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>despondingly</stage>
<line>You see</line>
<em>me here</em>
.</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sal.</speaker>
<line>I'd rather see you <em>thus</em>!</line></sp>
<stage>He draws out the weapon from the wound, and dies.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And</line>
<em>thus</em>
I will be seen; unless the succour,
<line>The last frail reed of our beleagured hopes, </line>
<line>Arrive with Ofratanes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Did you not </line>
<line>Receive a token from your dying brother, </line>
<line>Appointing Zames chief?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I did.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Where's Zames?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Dead.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					And Altada?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Dying.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Pania? Sfero?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Pania yet lives; but Sfero's fled or captive. </line>
<line>I am alone.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					And is all lost?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Our walls, </line>
<line>Though thinly manned, may still hold out against </line>
<line>Their present force, or aught save treachery: </line>
<line>But i' the field---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>I thought 'twas the intent </line>
<line>Of Salemenes not to risk a sally </line>
<line>Till ye were strengthened by the expected succours.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker><line>I over-ruled him.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
Well, the
<em>fault's</em>
a brave one.</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>But fatal. Oh, my brother! I would give </line>
<line>These realms, of which thou wert the ornament, </line>
<line>The sword and shield, the sole-redeeming honour, </line>
<line>To call back---But I will not weep for thee; </line>
<line>Thou shalt be mourned for as thou wouldst be mourned. </line>
<line>It grieves me most that thou couldst quit this life </line>
<line>Believing that I could survive what thou </line>
<line>Hast died for---our long royalty of race. </line>
<line>If I redeem it, I will give thee blood </line>
<line>Of thousands, tears of millions, for atonement, </line>
<line>(The tears of all the good are thine already). </line>
<line>If not, we meet again soon,---if the spirit </line>
<line>Within us lives beyond:---thou readest mine, </line>
<line>And dost me justice now. Let me once clasp </line>
<line>That yet warm hand, and fold that throbless heart </line>
<stage>Embraces the body.</stage>
<line>To this which beats so bitterly. Now, bear</line> 
<line>The body hence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sol.</speaker>
<line>Where?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>To my proper chamber. </line>
<line>Place it beneath my canopy, as though </line>
<line>The King lay there: when this is done, we will </line>
<line>Speak further of the rites due to such ashes.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exeunt Soldiers with the body of <strong>Salemenes</strong></stage>
    <stage>Enter. <strong>Pania</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Well, Pania! have you placed the guards, and issued </line>
<line>The orders fixed on?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Sire, I have obeyed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And do the soldiers keep their hearts up?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					Sire?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I am answered! When a king asks twice, and has</line> 
<line>A question as an answer to <em>his</em> question,</line>
<line>It is a portent. What! they are disheartened?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>The death of Salemenes, and the shouts </line>
<line>Of the exulting rebels on his fall, </line>
<line>Have made them---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<em>Rage</em>
---not droop---it should have been.
<line>We'll find the means to rouse them.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Such a loss </line>
<line>Might sadden even a victory.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Alas! </line>
<line>Who can so feel it as I feel? but yet, </line>
<line>Though cooped within these walls, they are strong, and we </line>
<line>Have those without will break their way through hosts, </line>
<line>To make their sovereign's dwelling what it was--- </line>
<line>A palace, not a prison---nor a fortress.</line></sp>
<stage><em>Enter an Officer, hastily.</em></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Thy face seems ominous. Speak!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Offi.</speaker>
<line>I dare not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Dare not? </line>
<line>While millions dare revolt with sword in hand! </line>
<line>That's strange. I pray thee break that loyal silence </line>
<line>Which loathes to shock its sovereign; we can hear </line>
<line>Worse than thou hast to tell.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Proceed---thou hearest.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Offi.</speaker>
<line>The wall which skirted near the river's brink </line>
<line>Is thrown down by the sudden inundation </line>
<line>Of the Euphrates, which now rolling, swoln </line>
<line>From the enormous mountains where it rises, </line>
<line>By the late rains of that tempestuous region, </line>
<line>O'erfloods its banks, and hath destroyed the bulwark.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>That's a black augury! it has been said </line>
<line>For ages, "That the City ne'er should yield </line>
<line>"To man, until the River grew its foe."</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I can forgive the omen, not the ravage. </line>
<line>How much is swept down of the wall?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Offi.</speaker>
<line>					About </line>
<line>Some twenty stadia.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And all this is left </line>
<line>Pervious to the assailants?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Offi.</speaker>
<line>					For the present </line>
<line>The River's fury must impede the assault; </line>
<line>But when he shrinks into his wonted channel, </line>
<line>And may be crossed by the accustomed barks, </line>
<line>The palace is their own.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>That shall be never. </line>
<line>Though men, and gods, and elements, and omens, </line>
<line>Have risen up 'gainst one who ne'er provoked them, </line>
<line>My father's house shall never be a cave </line>
<line>For wolves to horde and howl in.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>With your sanction, </line>
<line>I will proceed to the spot, and take such measures </line>
<line>For the assurance of the vacant space </line>
<line>As time and means permit.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>About it straight, </line>
<line>And bring me back, as speedily as full </line>
<line>And fair investigation may permit, </line>
<line>Report of the true state of this irruption </line>
<line>Of waters. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exeunt <strong>Pania</strong> and the Officer.
</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Thus the very waves rise up </line>
<line>Against you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>They are not my subjects, girl, </line>
<line>And may be pardoned, since they can't be punished.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>			I joy to see this portent shakes you not.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>I am past the fear of portents: they can tell me </line>
<line>Nothing I have not told myself since midnight: </line>
<line>Despair anticipates such things.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Despair!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No; not despair precisely. When we know </line>
<line>All that can come, and how to meet it, our </line>
<line>Resolves, if firm, may merit a more noble </line>
<line>Word than this is to give it utterance. </line>
<line>But what are words to us? we have well nigh done </line>
<line>With them and all things.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					</line>
Save
<em>one deed</em>
---the last
<line>And greatest to all mortals; crowning act </line>
<line>Of all that was, or is, or is to be--- </line>
<line>The only thing common to all mankind, </line>
<line>So different in their births, tongues, sexes, natures, </line>
<line>Hues, features, climes, times, feelings, intellects, </line>
<line>Without one point of union save in this--- </line>
<line>To which we tend, for which we're born, and thread </line>
<line>The labyrinth of mystery, called life.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Our clue being well nigh wound out, let's be cheerful. </line>
<line>They who have nothing more to fear may well </line>
<line>Indulge a smile at that which once appalled; </line>
<line>As children at discovered bugbears.</line></sp>
    <stage>Re-enter <strong>Pania</strong>.</stage>
    <sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis </line>
<line>As was reported: I have ordered there </line>
<line>A double guard, withdrawing from the wall, </line>
<line>Where it was strongest, the required addition </line>
<line>To watch the breach occasioned by the waters.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>You have done your duty faithfully, and as </line>
<line>My worthy Pania! further ties between us </line>
<line>Draw near a close---I pray you take this key: </line>
<stage>Gives a key.</stage>
<line>It opens to a secret chamber, placed</line> 
<line>Behind the couch in my own chamber---(Now </line>
<line>Pressed by a nobler weight than e'er it bore--- </line>
<line>Though a long line of sovereigns have lain down </line>
<line>Along its golden frame---as bearing for </line>
<line>A time what late was Salemenes.)---Search </line>
<line>The secret covert to which this will lead you; </line>
<line>'Tis full of treasure; take it for yourself </line>
<line>And your companions: there's enough to load ye, </line>
<line>Though ye be many. Let the slaves be freed, too; </line>
<line>And all the inmates of the palace, of </line>
<line>Whatever sex, now quit it in an hour. </line>
<line>Thence launch the regal barks, once formed for pleasure, </line>
<line>And now to serve for safety, and embark. </line>
<line>The river's broad and swoln, and uncommanded, </line>
<line>(More potent than a king) by these besiegers. </line>
<line>Fly! and be happy!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Under your protection! </line>
<line>So you accompany your faithful guard.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>No, Pania! that must not be; get thee hence, </line>
<line>And leave me to my fate.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis the first time </line>
<line>I ever disobeyed: but now---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>So all men </line>
<line>Dare beard me now, and Insolence within </line>
<line>Apes Treason from without. Question no further;</line> 
<line>'Tis my command, my last command. Wilt <em>thou</em></line>
<line>Oppose it? <em>thou!</em></line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>But yet---not yet.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Well, then, </line>
<line>Swear that you will obey when I shall give </line>
<line>The signal.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>With a heavy but true heart, </line>
<line>I promise.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>'Tis enough. Now order here </line>
<line>Faggots, pine-nuts, and withered leaves, and such </line>
<line>Things as catch fire and blaze with one sole spark; </line>
<line>Bring cedar, too, and precious drugs, and spices, </line>
<line>And mighty planks, to nourish a tall pile; </line>
<line>Bring frankincense and myrrh, too, for it is </line>
<line>For a great sacrifice I build the pyre! </line>
<line>And heap them round yon throne.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>My Lord!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					I have said it, </line>
<line>And <em>you</em> have sworn.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					And could keep my faith </line>
<line>Without a vow. </line></sp>
<stage>				Exit
<strong>Pania</strong></stage>
.
    <sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					What mean you?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>You shall know </line>
<line>Anon---what the whole earth shall ne'er forget.</line></sp>
    <stage><strong>Pania</strong>, returning with a Herald.</stage>
    <sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>My King, in going forth upon my duty,</line>
<line>This herald has been brought before me, craving </line>
<line>An audience.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Let him speak.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>The</line>
<em>King</em>
Arbaces---</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>What, crowned already?---But, proceed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>					Beleses, </line>
<line>The anointed High-priest---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Of what god or demon? </line>
<line>With new kings rise new altars. But, proceed; </line>
<line>You are sent to prate your master's will, and not </line>
<line>Reply to mine.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>And Satrap Ofratanes---</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Why, <em>he</em> is <em>ours</em></line></sp>
    <sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
        <stage>showing a ring.</stage>
<line>					Be sure that he is now</line> 
<line>In the camp of the conquerors; behold </line>
<line>His signet ring.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis his. A worthy triad! </line>
<line>Poor Salemenes! thou hast died in time </line>
<line>To see one treachery the less: this man </line>
<line>Was thy true friend and my most trusted subject. </line>
<line>Proceed.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>They offer thee thy life, and freedom </line>
<line>Of choice to single out a residence </line>
<line>In any of the further provinces, </line>
<line>Guarded and watched, but not confined in person, </line>
<line>Where thou shalt pass thy days in peace; but on </line>
<line>Condition that the three young princes are </line>
<line>Given up as hostages.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>ironically</stage>
<line>The generous Victors!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>I wait the answer.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Answer, slave! How long </line>
<line>Have slaves decided on the doom of kings?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>Since they were free.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Mouthpiece of mutiny! </line>
<line>Thou at the least shalt learn the penalty </line>
<line>Of treason, though its proxy only. Pania! </line>
<line>Let his head be thrown from our walls within </line>
<line>The rebels' lines, his carcass down the river. </line>
<line>Away with him! </line></sp>
<stage>				<strong>Pania</strong>
and the Guards seizing him.
</stage>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					I never yet obeyed </line>
<line>Your orders with more pleasure than the present. </line>
<line>Hence with him, soldiers! do not soil this hall </line>
<line>Of royalty with treasonable gore; </line>
<line>Put him to rest without.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>A single word: </line>
<line>My office, King, is sacred.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And what's</line>
<em>mine?</em>
<line>That thou shouldst come and dare to ask of me </line>
<line>To lay it down?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>I but obeyed my orders, </line>
<line>At the same peril if refused, as now </line>
<line>Incurred by my obedience.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>So there are </line>
<line>New monarchs of an hour's growth as despotic </line>
<line>As sovereigns swathed in purple, and enthroned </line>
<line>From birth to manhood!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>My life waits your breath. </line>
<line>Yours (I speak humbly)---but it may be---yours </line>
<line>May also be in danger scarce less imminent: </line>
<line>Would it then suit the last hours of a line </line>
<line>Such as is that of Nimrod, to destroy </line>
<line>A peaceful herald, unarmed, in his office; </line>
<line>And violate not only all that man </line>
<line>Holds sacred between man and man---but that </line>
<line>More holy tie which links us with the Gods?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>He's right.---Let him go free.---My life's last act </line>
<line>Shall not be one of wrath. Here, fellow, take </line>
<line>Gives him a golden cup from a table near.</line>
<line>This golden goblet, let it hold your wine, </line>
<line>And think of <em>me</em>; or melt it into ingots,</line>
<line>And think of nothing but their weight and value.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>I thank you doubly for my life, and this </line>
<line>Most gorgeous gift, which renders it more precious. </line>
<line>But must I bear no answer?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Yes,---I ask </line>
<line>An hour's truce to consider.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>But an hour's?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>An hour's: if at the expiration of </line>
<line>That time your masters hear no further from me, </line>
<line>They are to deem that I reject their terms, </line>
<line>And act befittingly.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>					I shall not fail </line>
<line>To be a faithful legate of your pleasure.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And hark! a word more.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>					I shall not forget it, </line>
<line>Whate'er it be.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Commend me to Beleses; </line>
<line>And tell him, ere a year expire, I summon </line>
<line>Him hence to meet me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>Where?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>At Babylon. </line>
<line>At least from thence he will depart to meet me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Her.</speaker>
<line>I shall obey you to the letter. </line></sp>
<stage>Exit Herald.</stage><sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Pania!--- </line>
<line>Now, my good Pania!---quick---with what I ordered.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>My Lord,---the soldiers are already charged.</line></sp>
<line>And see! they enter.</line>
<stage><em>Soldiers enter, and form a Pile about the Throne, etc.</em></stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Higher, my good soldiers, </line>
<line>And thicker yet; and see that the foundation </line>
<line>Be such as will not speedily exhaust </line>
<line>Its own too subtle flame; nor yet be quenched </line>
<line>With aught officious aid would bring to quell it.</line> 
<line>Let the throne form the <em>core</em> of it; I would not</line>
<line>Leave that, save fraught with fire unquenchable, </line>
<line>To the new comers. Frame the whole as if </line>
<line>'Twere to enkindle the strong tower of our </line>
<line>Inveterate enemies. Now it bears an aspect! </line>
<line>How say you, Pania, will this pile suffice </line>
<line>For a King's obsequies?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Aye, for a kingdom's. </line>
<line>I understand you, now.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And blame me?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>No--- </line>
<line>Let me but fire the pile, and share it with you.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>That</line>
<em>duty's</em>
mine.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					A woman's!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>'Tis the soldier's</line> 
<line>Part to die <em>for</em> his sovereign, and why not</line>
<line>			The woman's with her lover?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>'Tis most strange!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>But not so rare, my Pania, as thou think'st it. </line>
<line>In the mean time, live thou.---Farewell! the pile </line>
<line>Is ready.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>					I should shame to leave my sovereign </line>
<line>With but a single female to partake </line>
<line>His death.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Too many far have heralded </line>
<line>Me to the dust already. Get thee hence; </line>
<line>Enrich thee.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>And live wretched!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Think upon </line>
<line>Thy vow:---'tis sacred and irrevocable.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>Since it is so, farewell.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Search well my chamber, </line>
<line>Feel no remorse at bearing off the gold; </line>
<line>Remember, what you leave you leave the slaves </line>
<line>Who slew me: and when you have borne away </line>
<line>All safe off to your boats, blow one long blast </line>
<line>Upon the trumpet as you quit the palace. </line>
<line>The river's brink is too remote, its stream </line>
<line>Too loud at present to permit the echo </line>
<line>To reach distinctly from its banks. Then fly,--- </line>
<line>And as you sail, turn back; but still keep on </line>
<line>Your way along the Euphrates: if you reach </line>
<line>The land of Paphlagonia, where the Queen </line>
<line>Is safe with my three sons in Cotta's court,</line> 
<line>Say what you <em>saw</em> at parting, and request</line>
<line>That she remember what I <em>said</em> at one</line>
<line>Parting more mournful still.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Pan.</speaker>
<line>That royal hand! </line>
<line>Let me then once more press it to my lips; </line>
<line>And these poor soldiers who throng round you, and </line>
<line>Would fain die with you!</line></sp>
<stage>The Soldiers and <strong>Pania</strong> throng round him, kissing his hand and the hem of his robe.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					My best! my last friends! </line>
<line>Let's not unman each other: part at once: </line>
<line>All farewells should be sudden, when for ever, </line>
<line>Else they make an eternity of moments, </line>
<line>And clog the last sad sands of life with tears. </line>
<line>Hence, and be happy: trust me, I am not </line>
<line><em>Now</em> to be pitied; or far more for what</line>
<line>Is past than present;---for the future, 'tis </line>
<line>In the hands of the deities, if such </line>
<line>There be: I shall know soon. Farewell---Farewell.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exeunt <strong>Pania</strong> and Soldiers.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>These men were honest: it is comfort still </line>
<line>That our last looks should be on loving faces.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And <em>lovely</em> ones, my beautiful!---but hear me!</line>
<line>If at this moment,---for we now are on </line>
<line>The brink,---thou feel'st an inward shrinking from </line>
<line>This leap through flame into the future, say it: </line>
<line>I shall not love thee less; nay, perhaps more, </line>
<line>For yielding to thy nature: and there's time </line>
<line>Yet for thee to escape hence.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Shall I light </line>
<line>One of the torches which lie heaped beneath </line>
<line>The ever-burning lamp that burns without, </line>
<line>Before Baal's shrine, in the adjoining hall?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Do so. Is that thy answer?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Thou shalt see.</line></sp>
<stage>				Exit <strong>Myrrha</strong>.</stage>
<sp><speaker>
Sar.
</speaker><stage>solus</stage><line>She's firm. My fathers! whom I will rejoin, </line>
<line>It may be, purified by death from some </line>
<line>Of the gross stains of too material being, </line>
<line>I would not leave your ancient first abode </line>
<line>To the defilement of usurping bondmen; </line>
<line>If I have not kept your inheritance </line>
<line>As ye bequeathed it, this bright part of it, </line>
<line>Your treasure---your abode---your sacred relics </line>
<line>Of arms, and records---monuments, and spoils,</line> 
<line>In which <em>they</em> would have revelled, I bear with me</line>
<line>To you in that absorbing element, </line>
<line>Which most personifies the soul as leaving </line>
<line>The least of matter unconsumed before </line>
<line>Its fiery workings:---and the light of this </line>
<line>Most royal of funereal pyres shall be </line>
<line>Not a mere pillar formed of cloud and flame, </line>
<line>A beacon in the horizon for a day, </line>
<line>And then a mount of ashes---but a light </line>
<line>To lesson ages, rebel nations, and </line>
<line>Voluptuous princes. Time shall quench full many </line>
<line>A people's records, and a hero's acts; </line>
<line>Sweep empire after empire, like this first </line>
<line>Of empires, into nothing; but even then </line>
<line>Shall spare this deed of mine, and hold it up </line>
<line>A problem few dare imitate, and none </line>
<line>Despise---but, it may be, avoid the life </line>
<line>Which led to such a consummation.</line></sp>
    <stage><strong>Myrrha</strong> returns with a lighted Torch in one Hand, and a Cup in the other.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Lo! </line>
<line>I've lit the lamp which lights us to the stars.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And the cup?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis my country's custom to </line>
<line>Make a libation to the Gods.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					And mine </line>
<line>To make libations amongst men. I've not </line>
<line>Forgot the custom; and although alone, </line>
<line>Will drain one draught in memory of many </line>
<line>A joyous banquet past.</line>
<stage><strong>Sardanapalus</strong>
takes the cup, and after drinking and tinkling the reversed cup, as a drop falls, exclaims---</stage>
<line>					And this libation</line>
<line>Is for the excellent Beleses.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Why </line>
<line>Dwells thy mind rather upon that man's name </line>
<line>Than on his mate's in villany?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>The other </line>
<line>Is a mere soldier, a mere tool, a kind </line>
<line>Of human sword in a friend's hand; the other </line>
<line>Is master-mover of his warlike puppet; </line>
<line>But I dismiss them from my mind.---Yet pause, </line>
<line>My Myrrha! dost thou truly follow me, </line>
<line>Freely and fearlessly?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And dost thou think </line>
<line>A Greek girl dare not do for love, that which </line>
<line>An Indian widow braves for custom?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Then </line>
<line>We but await the signal.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>It is long </line>
<line>In sounding.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Now, farewell; one last embrace.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Embrace, but</line>
<em>not</em>
the last; there is one more.
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>True, the commingling fire will mix our ashes.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>And pure as is my love to thee, shall they, </line>
<line>Purged from the dross of earth, and earthly passion, </line>
<line>Mix pale with thine. A single thought yet irks me.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>Say it.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>It is that no kind hand will gather </line>
<line>The dust of both into one urn.</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					The better: </line>
<line>Rather let them be borne abroad upon </line>
<line>The winds of heaven, and scattered into air, </line>
<line>Than be polluted more by human hands </line>
<line>Of slaves and traitors. In this blazing palace, </line>
<line>And its enormous walls of reeking ruin, </line>
<line>We leave a nobler monument than Egypt </line>
<line>Hath piled in her brick mountains, o'er dead kings,</line> 
<line>Or <em>kine</em>---for none know whether those proud piles</line>
<line>Be for their monarch, or their ox-god Apis: </line>
<line>So much for monuments that have forgotten </line>
<line>Their very record!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Then farewell, thou earth! </line>
<line>And loveliest spot of earth! farewell, Ionia! </line>
<line>Be thou still free and beautiful, and far </line>
<line>Aloof from desolation! My last prayer </line>
<line>Was for thee, my last thoughts, save <em>one</em>, were of thee!</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>And that?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					Is yours.</line></sp>
<stage>				The trumpet of <strong>Pania</strong> sounds without.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Hark!</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line><em>Now!</em></line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>					Adieu, Assyria! </line>
<line>I loved thee well, my own, my fathers' land, </line>
<line>And better as my country than my kingdom. </line>
<line>I sated thee with peace and joys; and this </line>
<line>Is my reward! and now I owe thee nothing, </line>
<line>Not even a grave. </line>
<stage>He mounts the pile.</stage>
<line>			Now, Myrrha!</line></sp>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>Art thou ready?</line>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Sar.</speaker>
<line>As the torch in thy grasp.</line></sp>
<stage><strong>Myrrha</strong> fires the pile.</stage>
<sp><speaker>Myr.</speaker>
<line>					'Tis fired! I come.</line></sp>
<stage>As <strong>Myrrha</strong>springs forward to throw herself into the flames, the Curtain falls.</stage></div>
</div>
</play>
</xml>	